<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<csand-standard xmlns="https://open.ribose.com/standards/csand">
<bibdata type="standard">
  <title language="en" format="text/plain">Cloud Controls Matrix 3.0.1 Consensus Assessment Questionnaire</title>
  <docidentifier type="csand">CCM-CAIQ-3.0.1</docidentifier>
  <docnumber>CCM-CAIQ-3.0.1</docnumber>
  <date type="published">
    <on>2019-04-30</on>
  </date>
  <contributor>
    <role type="author"/>
    <organization>
      <name>Ribose</name>
    </organization>
  </contributor>
  <contributor>
    <role type="publisher"/>
    <organization>
      <name>Ribose</name>
    </organization>
  </contributor>
  
  <language>en</language>
  <script>Latn</script><abstract>
  <p id="_c2363e94-276e-4f99-a1b4-0fa935ec73c1">&lt;Insert Abstract Text here&gt;</p>
</abstract>
  <status format="plain">draft</status>
  <copyright>
    <from>2019</from>
    <owner>
      <organization>
        <name>Ribose</name>
      </organization>
    </owner>
  </copyright>
  <editorialgroup>
    <committee/>
  </editorialgroup>
</bibdata>
<preface><abstract id="_abstract">
  <p id="_16f75077-7d65-47d4-b430-7890e353ed89">&lt;Insert Abstract Text here&gt;</p>
</abstract><foreword obligation="informative"><title>Preface</title><note id="_e4cce5cd-b138-4852-9aea-75d9f42ab50e">
  <p id="_14afd0df-468e-4d1c-8c6d-fdc8e24d8ae1">Insert Preface Text here. Give CSA specific commentary: describe the technical content, reason for document, history of the document and precursors, and plans for future work.</p>
</note>
<p id="_a55527fb-cc66-40c4-93e6-1074373925d3">Attention is drawn to the possibility that some of the elements of this document may be the subject of patent rights. The Open Geospatial Consortium shall not be held responsible for identifying any or all such patent rights.</p>
<p id="_37022827-f098-4781-89bd-02addd822e57">Recipients of this document are requested to submit, with their comments, notification of any relevant patent claims or other intellectual property rights of which they may be aware that might be infringed by any implementation of the standard set forth in this document, and to provide supporting documentation.</p></foreword></preface><sections>

<clause id="_scope" obligation="normative">
  <title>Scope</title>
  <note id="_712d654f-d17d-4be8-98b8-61c7ca645afc">
  <p id="_a54c8fde-2428-4857-bd0c-db94dc27e1fa">Insert Scope text here. Give the subject of the document and the aspects of that scope covered by the document.</p>
</note>
</clause>

<terms id="_terms_and_definitions" obligation="normative"><title>Terms and definitions</title>

<term id="_example_term"><preferred>example term</preferred><definition><p id="_66fa7497-81e5-4084-ac5b-99915b43bd72">term used for exemplary purposes</p></definition>


<termnote id="_cb400399-29e5-4a92-bf72-acc72fd1d559">
  <p id="_008815d6-ef41-4124-9fca-0def8e0bb31d">An example note.</p>
</termnote><termexample id="_90ef3995-4b62-4e63-8d1a-4231d1b6cc35">
  <p id="_6cbd4713-074e-4e18-bce1-87ed99713c81">Here’s an example of an example term.</p>
</termexample><termsource status="identical">
  <origin bibitemid="ISO19101-1" type="inline" citeas="ISO 19101-1:2014"/>
</termsource></term></terms>
<clause id="_controls" obligation="normative"><title>Controls</title><requirement id="_f4430e7c-4a6e-434e-8dd5-98fbc320acd6" obligation="requirement"><title>Application &amp; Interface Security</title><label>AIS</label><requirement id="_9cab5ea8-18f0-4b7c-94aa-219581cedf22"><title>Application Security</title><label>AIS-01</label><description><p id="_8918006f-22af-43f6-b07d-c78218813d24">Applications and programming interfaces (APIs) shall be designed, developed, deployed, and tested in accordance with leading industry standards (e.g., OWASP for web applications) and adhere to applicable legal, statutory, or regulatory compliance obligations.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_9d1c9563-8665-4245-8c6b-f378c7757c0b">Do you use industry standards (Build Security in Maturity Model [BSIMM] benchmarks, Open Group ACS Trusted Technology Provider Framework, NIST, etc.) to build in security for your Systems/Software Development Lifecycle (SDLC)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_e75d64d8-392e-4f0e-ae9c-6b8fe5fb2f2b">Do you use an automated source code analysis tool to detect security defects in code prior to production?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_7b50eaf2-9755-4599-a3df-f6e8a9ed091a">Do you use manual source-code analysis to detect security defects in code prior to production?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_0ff1053b-2da7-4e68-9a36-1fbefc944eb5">Do you verify that all of your software suppliers adhere to industry standards for Systems/Software Development Lifecycle (SDLC) security?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_1d684cce-451a-4f38-a7e0-b631a7a9afc0">(SaaS only) Do you review your applications for security vulnerabilities and address any issues prior to deployment to production?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_74b5fe63-b259-4e67-a171-25466ec655c1"><title>Customer Access Requirements</title><label>AIS-02</label><description><p id="_e3db8835-fae4-481c-9728-7d82f05825bf">Prior to granting customers access to data, assets, and information systems, identified security, contractual, and regulatory requirements for customer access shall be addressed.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_08a6c03b-c280-485b-89bc-d702d72af893">Are all identified security, contractual, and regulatory requirements for customer access contractually addressed and remediated prior to granting customers access to data, assets, and information systems?</p>
</verification></requirement><description>
<p id="_cb3df704-9ef2-4873-9352-b40c089a3378">.</p>
</description><requirement id="_42ed5663-f5f0-4994-9137-c6881e7e0ce3">
<label>AIS- 02</label>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_35b969ad-176c-4f00-b1fb-e464817df488">Are all requirements and trust levels for customers’ access defined and documented?</p>
</verification>
</requirement>
<requirement id="_bc4d0bed-3e92-4a3f-9bfd-68701c67ca3f"><title>Data Integrity</title><label>AIS-03</label><description><p id="_8b02cde7-04f5-4d10-8a8c-ab3e51233310">Data input and output integrity routines (i.e., reconciliation and edit checks) shall be implemented for application interfaces and databases to prevent manual or systematic processing errors, corruption of data, or misuse.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_8538eb20-dfc2-4a08-8dea-447c758e702c">Are data input and output integrity routines (i.e., reconciliation and edit checks) implemented for application interfaces and databases to prevent manual or systematic processing errors or corruption of data?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_16594e1d-e691-421b-bc60-63a24d6fabce"><title>Data Security / Integrity</title><label>AIS-04</label><description><p id="_b5686410-1da9-49f3-baf5-fe85b3afd383">Policies and procedures shall be established and maintained in support of data security to include (confidentiality, integrity, and availability) across multiple system interfaces, jurisdictions, and business functions to prevent improper disclosure, alternation, or destruction.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_7f3618a5-c757-4c52-a961-6e83aba927d5">Is your Data Security Architecture designed using an industry standard (e.g., CDSA, MULITSAFE, CSA Trusted Cloud Architectural Standard, FedRAMP, CAESARS)?</p>
</verification></requirement></requirement>
<requirement id="_3a4a0f1b-990b-4701-ae0c-0bf4cb4b2b00" obligation="requirement"><title>Audit Assurance &amp; Compliance</title><label>AAC</label><requirement id="_28ec1c4a-f5da-4929-93bc-a2e55447bdbe"><title>Audit Planning</title><label>AAC-01</label><description><p id="_176f8f06-ed6d-4b19-b418-46556e03f6c8">Audit plans shall be developed and maintained to address business process disruptions. Auditing plans shall focus on reviewing the effectiveness of the implementation of security operations. All audit activities must be agreed upon prior to executing any audits.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_c8cf041a-1177-4281-a7fe-9fee800a56ba">Do you produce audit assertions using a structured, industry accepted format (e.g., CloudAudit/A6 URI Ontology, CloudTrust, SCAP/CYBEX, GRC XML, ISACA’s Cloud Computing Management Audit/Assurance Program, etc.)?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_606fbed1-ffb0-420a-aaa0-15a3aef84cdf"><title>Independent Audits</title><label>AAC-02</label><description><p id="_7bed0d4d-21b6-48d4-8fdd-066797ab3a8c">Independent reviews and assessments shall be performed at least annually to ensure that the organization addresses nonconformities of established policies, standards, procedures, and compliance obligations.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_7e1cc3dc-1ccd-418f-bf3f-b256ad099573">Do you allow tenants to view your SOC2/ISO 27001 or similar third-party audit or certification reports?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_4cafab64-e29d-41f9-84d0-82645c0f89c0">Do you conduct network penetration tests of your cloud service infrastructure regularly as prescribed by industry best practices and guidance?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_8432b0f1-4b9b-460e-9e4a-c9da7b0c3027">Do you conduct application penetration tests of your cloud infrastructure regularly as prescribed by industry best practices and guidance?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_f02365f7-ffbe-48dd-9b82-68cebaecaf47">Do you conduct internal audits regularly as prescribed by industry best practices and guidance?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_1d386847-85b1-430d-b7d1-477d389d9d62">Do you conduct external audits regularly as prescribed by industry best practices and guidance?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_1a2082b2-ae01-4ae8-b15d-967bb21a2b16">Are the results of the penetration tests available to tenants at their request?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_a86e4c49-7b32-4ef2-a41e-39b6c12babe6">Are the results of internal and external audits available to tenants at their request?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_168e5328-1585-4c06-8f7b-f21c7dc338ae">Do you have an internal audit program that allows for cross-functional audit of assessments?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_dec88ffe-e3d1-4f20-b3b9-8ec38166c966"><title>Information System Regulatory Mapping</title><label>AAC-03</label><description><p id="_7f8b9e73-e06d-4813-b5ea-be822c4a89ed">Organizations shall create and maintain a control framework which captures standards, regulatory, legal, and statutory requirements relevant for their business needs. The control framework shall be reviewed at least annually to ensure changes that could affect the business processes are reflected.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_17f3bb7f-77c2-4640-9edc-e413b565ba67">Do you have the ability to logically segment or encrypt customer data such that data may be produced for a single tenant only, without inadvertently accessing another tenant’s data?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_69fc3734-432d-4d42-bbba-8b1af3fd23c4">Do you have the capability to recover data for a specific customer in the case of a failure or data loss?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_97ed5cce-5068-4ddf-a7af-e9f6ff98a01f">Do you have the capability to restrict the storage of customer data to specific countries or geographic locations?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_8e599d7f-504e-482f-84be-f092fb841d52">Do you have a program in place that includes the ability to monitor changes to the regulatory requirements in relevant jurisdictions, adjust your security program for changes to legal requirements, and ensure compliance with relevant regulatory requirements?</p>
</verification></requirement></requirement>
<requirement id="_f57570ee-e485-4ccc-bae6-46565698b6ee" obligation="requirement"><title>Business Continuity Management &amp; Operational Resilience</title><label>BCR</label><requirement id="_8074bab9-208d-4f04-8e97-c8e02b994470"><title>Business Continuity Planning</title><label>BCR-01</label><description><p id="_48f3d667-da55-4365-ae7a-b4613b9b642e">A consistent unified framework for business continuity planning and plan development shall be established, documented, and adopted to ensure all business continuity plans are consistent in addressing priorities for testing, maintenance, and information security requirements. Requirements for business continuity plans include the following:</p>
<ul id="_6c94c51b-9c6a-4171-aa63-7a9dba337f39">
  <li>
    <p id="_53f1bcfc-07fb-46bd-886f-48fd2da31ccf">Defined purpose and scope, aligned with relevant dependencies</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_97005381-a9d1-49c5-9608-b40856934530">Accessible to and understood by those who will use them</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_a71337ab-36b7-4ec0-b135-025db5962ca3">Owned by a named person(s) who is responsible for their review, update, and approval</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_99604941-0a9b-4b55-b8ce-3115461cadc7">Defined lines of communication, roles, and responsibilities</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_2757d6a1-3d84-4799-82f1-e8f829a6c07b">Detailed recovery procedures, manual work-around, and reference information</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_de5b94eb-0a60-4e08-a82a-224a56878280">Method for plan invocation</p>
  </li>
</ul>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_40d0375e-c994-482f-a7a2-709d68b5baa8">Do you provide tenants with geographically resilient hosting options?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_6af245b8-7a6c-455c-8096-46a9e80fd947">Do you provide tenants with infrastructure service failover capability to other providers?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_f0139b89-ac7d-46f8-9b03-ed93b8fa8c6c"><title>Business Continuity Testing</title><label>BCR-02</label><description><p id="_b362d136-c3db-47eb-a8e6-4c1aa0f4846a">Business continuity and security incident response plans shall be subject to testing at planned intervals or upon significant organizational or environmental changes. Incident response plans shall involve impacted customers (tenant) and other business relationships that represent critical intra-supply chain business process dependencies.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_dc92014d-e241-45e4-bdff-96e2fbdcdbd9">Are business continuity plans subject to testing at planned intervals or upon significant organizational or environmental changes to ensure continuing effectiveness?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_05a27b31-c8df-4db9-9444-b421c8cddf84"><title>Power / Telecommunications</title><label>BCR-03</label><description><p id="_9823a68a-66b5-4dcf-9a2b-5a0530e0f31b">Data center utilities services and environmental conditions (e.g., water, power, temperature and humidity controls, telecommunications, and internet connectivity) shall be secured, monitored, maintained, and tested for continual effectiveness at planned intervals to ensure protection from unauthorized interception or damage, and designed with automated fail-over or other redundancies in the event of planned or unplanned disruptions.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_b225b971-1649-4844-a0a7-58d850f8242c">Do you provide tenants with documentation showing the transport route of their data between your systems?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_30739ec3-e0fa-44cd-a16a-3a76c178a00d">Can tenants define how their data is transported and through which legal jurisdictions?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_fe022494-5a30-44b8-adfa-bb59afc85718"><title>Documentation</title><label>BCR-04</label><description><p id="_5a77170e-22cc-4b61-89f5-671722aeb629">Information system documentation (e.g., administrator and user guides, and architecture diagrams) shall be made available to authorized personnel to ensure the following:</p>
<ul id="_7683ab9a-1749-4b96-8566-222fff06495b">
  <li>
    <p id="_019776f7-7391-4305-82f7-7a9fc1d2744b">Configuring, installing, and operating the information system</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_f6d44f8f-9134-4824-8418-6e530fc99fc0">Effectively using the system’s security features</p>
  </li>
</ul>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_f5b106b1-83ca-40aa-a354-4edbe69aefdf">Are information system documents (e.g., administrator and user guides, architecture diagrams, etc.) made available to authorized personnel to ensure configuration, installation and operation of the information system?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_003f0f11-bad0-4c9c-aedb-ee9d73a00fee"><title>Environmental Risks</title><label>BCR-05</label><description><p id="_646ae890-e6ad-46f3-84c3-328bb6173715">Physical protection against damage from natural causes and disasters, as well as deliberate attacks, including fire, flood, atmospheric electrical discharge, solar induced geomagnetic storm, wind, earthquake, tsunami, explosion, nuclear accident, volcanic activity, biological hazard, civil unrest, mudslide, tectonic activity, and other forms of natural or man-made disaster shall be anticipated, designed, and have countermeasures applied.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_5fc3f4dd-4393-45aa-8624-2cf4c39ec73c">Is physical protection against damage (e.g., natural causes, natural disasters, deliberate attacks) anticipated and designed with countermeasures applied?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_368252a2-f7b5-48f9-935c-e04c2bab59fc"><title>Equipment Location</title><label>BCR-06</label><description><p id="_392d895a-2cfa-4756-8c17-a1c82f2d8949">To reduce the risks from environmental threats, hazards, and opportunities for unauthorized access, equipment shall be kept away from locations subject to high probability environmental risks and supplemented by redundant equipment located at a reasonable distance.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_d2abd916-2f13-4daf-bb8c-78849f0943e9">Are any of your data centers located in places that have a high probability/occurrence of high-impact environmental risks (floods, tornadoes, earthquakes, hurricanes, etc.)?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_9b423154-398f-4ef0-ba0d-1801436caa51"><title>Equipment Maintenance</title><label>BCR-07</label><description><p id="_9de7eb2a-73ca-443a-800b-311375022d39">Policies and procedures shall be established, and supporting business processes and technical measures implemented, for equipment maintenance ensuring continuity and availability of operations and support personnel.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_e86b2cbf-a421-447b-80de-0bc06dc4fffc">If using virtual infrastructure, does your cloud solution include independent hardware restore and recovery capabilities?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_1df933f9-da04-4dd3-a631-f75e6f0cfbe3">If using virtual infrastructure, do you provide tenants with a capability to restore a Virtual Machine to a previous state in time?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_9e6d0c5c-84ba-436f-9805-f46a89f5aa2b">If using virtual infrastructure, do you allow virtual machine images to be downloaded and ported to a new cloud provider?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_dbf526ff-3397-4085-acd4-844b610c26b4">If using virtual infrastructure, are machine images made available to the customer in a way that would allow the customer to replicate those images in their own off-site storage location?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_381b4649-44b2-4cef-9f7e-3e90d8465cb7">Does your cloud solution include software/provider independent restore and recovery capabilities?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_8389e9c2-61ad-4c56-976e-95d66a33af39"><title>Equipment Power Failures</title><label>BCR-08</label><description><p id="_4d26f96c-a5ee-4db0-aff5-5f1a37e5ac77">Protection measures shall be put into place to react to natural and man-made threats based upon a geographically-specific business impact assessment.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_563edfb5-bb06-4ce2-99e5-bd374c6e13cb">Are security mechanisms and redundancies implemented to protect equipment from utility service outages (e.g., power failures, network disruptions, etc.)?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_e259b394-0954-4080-ab42-771c09a27804"><title>Impact Analysis</title><label>BCR-09</label><description><p id="_66a0331b-6606-4216-8431-3396a8477e1e">There shall be a defined and documented method for determining the impact of any disruption to the organization (cloud provider, cloud consumer) that must incorporate the following:</p>
<ul id="_6d787541-8d90-4560-bfc2-52cf87e260d3">
  <li>
    <p id="_f518a9cf-54e9-4456-87ac-6670316f34ca">Identify critical products and services</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_2c6482b0-398a-4579-9f89-239d062ca03c">Identify all dependencies, including processes, applications, business partners, and third party service providers</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_f037dd4e-3c40-4bef-9aec-0d81c3d3c965">Understand threats to critical products and services</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_bd2b67f0-f602-4c58-ba72-30e664a19908">Determine impacts resulting from planned or unplanned disruptions and how these vary over time</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_e1e37636-c9f4-45c4-af88-f7f4e0417de3">Establish the maximum tolerable period for disruption</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_4ca92510-5f66-4e7e-ac7c-8dfbe4335395">Establish priorities for recovery</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_b2d9f198-37ad-46ef-85a4-8e259cbacffb">Establish recovery time objectives for resumption of critical products and services within their maximum tolerable period of disruption</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_41f6032c-0682-483c-ada5-67fb58174287">Estimate the resources required for resumption</p>
  </li>
</ul>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_dac55547-afd4-4eb7-82db-71dbbd57a191">Do you provide tenants with ongoing visibility and reporting of your operational Service Level Agreement (SLA) performance?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_9907aaee-24af-421c-85ec-0690d3f1869e">Do you make standards-based information security metrics (CSA, CAMM, etc.) available to your tenants?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_9dbbe0f2-b86f-48e8-85d9-4cbff60279e0">Do you provide customers with ongoing visibility and reporting of your SLA performance?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_4512226e-49fe-4d33-a1cf-5a3758113e06"><title>Policy</title><label>BCR-10</label><description><p id="_8ff823de-f1ff-4473-bf24-84bea8e7b5a5">Policies and procedures shall be established, and supporting business processes and technical measures implemented, for appropriate IT governance and service management to ensure appropriate planning, delivery and support of the organization’s IT capabilities supporting business functions, workforce, and/or customers based on industry acceptable standards (i.e., ITIL v4 and COBIT 5). Additionally, policies and procedures shall include defined roles and responsibilities supported by regular workforce training.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_5b9ff718-758b-4e3c-8785-59b9972665a6">Are policies and procedures established and made available for all personnel to adequately support services operations’ roles?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_e5e2fc92-379e-444d-9e16-993a478e835f"><title>Retention Policy</title><label>BCR-11</label><description><p id="_bc56bd77-3eac-47c0-b214-6daf067b98b3">Policies and procedures shall be established, and supporting business processes and technical measures implemented, for defining and adhering to the retention period of any critical asset as per established policies and procedures, as well as applicable legal, statutory, or regulatory compliance obligations. Backup and recovery measures shall be incorporated as part of business continuity planning and tested accordingly for effectiveness.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_48f36bde-9579-4027-9ac6-745380f592f3">Do you have technical control capabilities to enforce tenant data retention policies?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_0c5256ba-4953-42eb-8b88-0c4d54dd3022">Do you have a documented procedure for responding to requests for tenant data from governments or third parties?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_208ecd65-d66f-4505-b90a-4720f18792e3">Have you implemented backup or redundancy mechanisms to ensure compliance with regulatory, statutory, contractual or business requirements?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_338830b1-6233-411b-85e9-16ffc62a69a3">Do you test your backup or redundancy mechanisms at least annually?</p>
</verification></requirement></requirement>
<requirement id="_af429ed8-98c3-4702-92e1-8c28626b16de" obligation="requirement"><title>Change Control &amp; Configuration Management</title><label>CCC</label><requirement id="_0b6ea946-6d8e-4827-bcbe-f75cdf1a5154"><title>New Development / Acquisition</title><label>CCC-01</label><description><p id="_3de8b611-f773-482a-979b-50903b88cf13">Policies and procedures shall be established, and supporting business processes and technical measures implemented, to ensure the development and/or acquisition of new data, physical or virtual applications, infrastructure network and systems components, or any corporate, operations and/or data center facilities have been pre-authorized by the organization’s business leadership or other accountable business role or function.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_ed884135-b2ff-4069-be14-e25f29178035">Are policies and procedures established for management authorization for development or acquisition of new applications, systems, databases, infrastructure, services, operations and facilities?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_db642985-d93e-440b-93ca-d517b0c3a645">Is documentation available that describes the installation, configuration, and use of products/services/features?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_a6a31c8a-d688-4d54-a91f-1926ce14d2e3"><title>Outsourced Development</title><label>CCC-02</label><description><p id="_7bdbf727-0bc1-4c2e-a81a-c1a3e6088bc6">External business partners shall adhere to the same policies and procedures for change management, release, and testing as internal developers within the organization (e.g., ITIL service management processes).</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_5fd34a59-2242-495d-82cf-d367e76ce79b">Do you have controls in place to ensure that standards of quality are being met for all software development?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_adbfa66d-a055-4ce4-8654-9a93a314ddc3">Do you have controls in place to detect source code security defects for any outsourced software development activities?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_db773069-ce7f-4f6d-a2db-06498f6bac87"><title>Quality Testing</title><label>CCC-03</label><description><p id="_51f4e402-d921-411e-b121-a15dded8e55f">Organizations shall follow a defined quality change control and testing process (e.g., ITIL Service Management) with established baselines, testing, and release standards which focus on system availability, confidentiality, and integrity of systems and services.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_c7b0c469-a5d5-453d-8eb1-4d48caf61d1d">Do you provide your tenants with documentation that describes your quality assurance process?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_4ae564fd-b433-47cf-83da-3cef467ce912">Is documentation describing known issues with certain products/services available?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_eeb7038f-ead1-480b-9f4b-ec9252048bf7">Are there policies and procedures in place to triage and remedy reported bugs and security vulnerabilities for product and service offerings?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_cd3e8797-e79d-4b4d-8550-e7734179cf45">Are mechanisms in place to ensure that all debugging and test code elements are removed from released software versions?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_926b62b0-8fe3-42ca-a05f-dfaf1696733f"><title>Unauthorized Software Installations</title><label>CCC-04</label><description><p id="_a91d2dfe-19f6-403e-a117-08c1e408ba0b">Policies and procedures shall be established, and supporting business processes and technical measures implemented, to restrict the installation of unauthorized software on organizationally-owned or managed user end-point devices (e.g., issued workstations, laptops, and mobile devices) and IT infrastructure network and systems components.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_f9fa5f66-d8ff-4a6d-8341-ed7422f2e8db">Do you have controls in place to restrict and monitor the installation of unauthorized software onto your systems?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_5a4281d6-1de2-4c0a-8078-ac54eb8018cd"><title>Production Changes</title><label>CCC-05</label><description><p id="_66da1325-a16c-4acd-b9aa-8ae8d8698379">Policies and procedures shall be established for managing the risks associated with applying changes to:</p>
<ul id="_e1f10d1b-b56c-46f7-bbc9-f96752ae03df">
  <li>
    <p id="_b469b99f-4985-496a-825e-48519b857af3">Business-critical or customer (tenant)-impacting (physical and virtual) applications and system-system interface (API) designs and configurations.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_d29c837c-6920-4d27-9fcb-e1216335e536">Infrastructure network and systems components.</p>
  </li>
</ul>
<p id="_a25a5fcd-3fbb-4021-9db2-baab1dcc0ba9">Technical measures shall be implemented to provide assurance that all changes directly correspond to a registered change request, business-critical or customer (tenant), and/or authorization by, the customer (tenant) as per agreement (SLA) prior to deployment.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_792dfb19-3603-47a1-b959-5ca8e9c29fbe">Do you provide tenants with documentation that describes your production change management procedures and their roles/rights/responsibilities within it?</p>
</verification></requirement></requirement>
<requirement id="_bf6d09f7-c09a-4f43-aca5-685f30f433b3" obligation="requirement"><title>Data Security &amp; Information Lifecycle Management</title><label>DSI</label><requirement id="_e900dc6d-2448-4455-b1fb-2c3fe0d1ec74"><title>Classification</title><label>DSI-01</label><description><p id="_b65eead9-b3f3-43ca-a016-ee9a39ff47d9">Data and objects containing data shall be assigned a classification by the data owner based on data type, value, sensitivity, and criticality to the organization.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_d42cd653-1674-4595-990b-556a80992b6a">Do you provide a capability to identify virtual machines via policy tags/metadata (e.g., tags can be used to limit guest operating systems from booting/instantiating/transporting data in the wrong country)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_bed757ae-ecdc-4192-a999-20b17cba9db5">Do you provide a capability to identify hardware via policy tags/metadata/hardware tags (e.g., TXT/TPM, VN-Tag, etc.)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_44ae4420-4bc8-4008-973a-461d04168e24">Do you have a capability to use system geographic location as an authentication factor?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_0e9f1ec8-5e2e-4588-8019-8b7b77d625f6">Can you provide the physical location/geography of storage of a tenant’s data upon request?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_15b41f40-ecd4-4f67-9221-df010a435839">Can you provide the physical location/geography of storage of a tenant’s data in advance?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_b442fd79-ea59-4ae5-b220-eb9c41ed0132">Do you follow a structured data-labeling standard (e.g., ISO 15489, Oasis XML Catalog Specification, CSA data type guidance)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_7d88d87e-1422-44e4-afa0-7f153395e68b">Do you allow tenants to define acceptable geographical locations for data routing or resource instantiation?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_c21eb236-bf7e-4e61-a98d-053f2a0d5fe3"><title>Data Inventory / Flows</title><label>DSI-02</label><description><p id="_0b1d367a-7863-4bbd-967f-9cb1bba03f34">Policies and procedures shall be established, and supporting business processes and technical measures implemented, to inventory, document, and maintain data flows for data that is resident (permanently or temporarily) within the service’s geographically distributed (physical and virtual) applications and infrastructure network and systems components and/or shared with other third parties to ascertain any regulatory, statutory, or supply chain agreement (SLA) compliance impact, and to address any other business risks associated with the data. Upon request, provider shall inform customer (tenant) of compliance impact and risk, especially if customer data is used as part of the services.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_f797cd19-9d26-47bc-8023-fcfbafe19285">Do you inventory, document, and maintain data flows for data that is resident (permanent or temporary) within the services’ applications and infrastructure network and systems?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_59fc75a7-a029-4a6d-ba50-e1c93de37ce8">Can you ensure that data does not migrate beyond a defined geographical residency?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_2c835312-7e17-445c-a17d-827a183275da"><title>E-commerce Transactions</title><label>DSI-03</label><description><p id="_9aa6c0bb-2376-4171-ba6e-7efa55425114">Data related to electronic commerce (e-commerce) that traverses public networks shall be appropriately classified and protected from fraudulent activity, unauthorized disclosure, or modification in such a manner to prevent contract dispute and compromise of data.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_498a0b20-2d3c-40c6-972e-a664a7f1ab07">Do you provide open encryption methodologies (3.4ES, AES, etc.) to tenants in order for them to protect their data if it is required to move through public networks (e.g., the Internet)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_bb808499-c6c0-4cc9-92fb-d2283bf932d4">Do you utilize open encryption methodologies any time your infrastructure components need to communicate with each other via public networks (e.g., Internet-based replication of data from one environment to another)?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_a78bfd63-1f86-4048-9da4-9aa805164e48"><title>Handling / Labeling / Security Policy</title><label>DSI-04</label><description><p id="_80e4184f-6c2a-440f-94c4-33b8039f19ff">Policies and procedures shall be established for labeling, handling, and the security of data and objects which contain data. Mechanisms for label inheritance shall be implemented for objects that act as aggregate containers for data.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_73704562-7cee-474c-bf06-0057249e0815">Are policies and procedures established for labeling, handling and the security of data and objects that contain data?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_435f7625-1645-405c-9fa3-02e1b5160186">Are mechanisms for label inheritance implemented for objects that act as aggregate containers for data?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_4d906507-4e45-4a5f-8386-1ff37341818e"><title>Nonproduction Data</title><label>DSI-05</label><description><p id="_a34a4c3e-f0fa-4ab9-bda9-48eca82deab7">Production data shall not be replicated or used in non-production environments. Any use of customer data in non-production environments requires explicit, documented approval from all customers whose data is affected, and must comply with all legal and regulatory requirements for scrubbing of sensitive data elements.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_868868d4-e833-4a58-b320-a3e8c2f26729">Do you have procedures in place to ensure production data shall not be replicated or used in non-production environments?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_5f4cc72f-7505-4c09-aa63-60c85e32533e"><title>Ownership / Stewardship</title><label>DSI-06</label><description><p id="_b6a884b1-f1de-4b42-83ff-6737d8f64ac4">All data shall be designated with stewardship, with assigned responsibilities defined, documented, and communicated.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_e138e750-a02f-4a34-a29c-5f7fed9b9d8c">Are the responsibilities regarding data stewardship defined, assigned, documented, and communicated?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_4ec382ec-65df-4d20-972c-833f48c9d360"><title>Secure Disposal</title><label>DSI-07</label><description><p id="_5dac6856-0013-42d8-b56c-91cd006fd7b8">Policies and procedures shall be established with supporting business processes and technical measures implemented for the secure disposal and complete removal of data from all storage media, ensuring data is not recoverable by any computer forensic means.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_12d4193e-4ef3-459e-bfd4-1db36c5de191">Do you support secure deletion (e.g., degaussing/cryptographic wiping) of archived and backed-up data as determined by the tenant?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_4421ec6b-2355-4640-a8e4-770bef495bec">Can you provide a published procedure for exiting the service arrangement, including assurance to sanitize all computing resources of tenant data once a customer has exited your environment or has vacated a resource?</p>
</verification></requirement></requirement>
<requirement id="_b61b2f6d-74a3-4da3-b170-ee0a55a96d07" obligation="requirement"><title>Datacenter Security</title><label>DCS</label><requirement id="_acc458d0-72ce-4a03-945a-54b29d2e81af"><title>Asset Management</title><label>DCS-01</label><description><p id="_575a1ef2-2663-4afe-932b-2f0a3f010779">Assets must be classified in terms of business criticality, service-level expectations, and operational continuity requirements. A complete inventory of business-critical assets located at all sites and/or geographical locations and their usage over time shall be maintained and updated regularly, and assigned ownership by defined roles and responsibilities.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_f57363d0-fa0f-42f4-b06c-056330054697">Do you maintain a complete inventory of all of your critical assets that includes ownership of the asset?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_95bf3fb3-b7ed-4d35-b334-1ec1be8e8533">Do you maintain a complete inventory of all of your critical supplier relationships?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_6172e6af-78ed-4a2e-a480-7d99f06ca437"><title>Controlled Access Points</title><label>DCS-02</label><description><p id="_2ca79aaa-47d4-4d84-82b0-164ee2999e91">Physical security perimeters (e.g., fences, walls, barriers, guards, gates, electronic surveillance, physical authentication mechanisms, reception desks, and security patrols) shall be implemented to safeguard sensitive data and information systems.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_1865a7de-0abb-482d-9440-a0d280c9f4cb">Are physical security perimeters (e.g., fences, walls, barriers, guards, gates, electronic surveillance, physical authentication mechanisms, reception desks, and security patrols) implemented?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_99ee7878-a055-4218-a7b7-a43a9b364583"><title>Equipment Identification</title><label>DCS-03</label><description><p id="_a373d6d5-9264-4466-927f-51f2a07a6fe5">Automated equipment identification shall be used as a method of connection authentication. Location-aware technologies may be used to validate connection authentication integrity based on known equipment location.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_c2fae2d8-4773-4052-ba0e-efa25df48693">Is automated equipment identification used as a method to validate connection authentication integrity based on known equipment location?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_65c138e8-f2ff-4f75-8656-7129aff77544"><title>Offsite Authorization</title><label>DCS-04</label><description><p id="_11fd62a6-fb0e-4a72-847d-18aa22679b4a">Authorization must be obtained prior to relocation or transfer of hardware, software, or data to an offsite premises.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_11edd060-bfef-4153-8569-9d023fb14ec3">Do you provide tenants with documentation that describes scenarios in which data may be moved from one physical location to another (e.g., offsite backups, business continuity failovers, replication)?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_f7ad9561-6654-4195-92f3-da6c69705d05"><title>Offsite Equipment</title><label>DCS-05</label><description><p id="_b4e4f70b-4649-4e3b-834a-80580cbcdb2b">Policies and procedures shall be established for the secure disposal of equipment (by asset type) used outside the organization’s premise. This shall include a wiping solution or destruction process that renders recovery of information impossible. The erasure shall consist of a full write of the drive to ensure that the erased drive is released to inventory for reuse and deployment or securely stored until it can be destroyed.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_12fa02f8-668e-4710-aa87-54b57037a0c4">Can you provide tenants with evidence documenting your policies and procedures governing asset management and repurposing of equipment?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_d866ec7b-23b3-46cc-b82d-b50e4a2941ef"><title>Policy</title><label>DCS-06</label><description><p id="_8cebee2f-2f58-4ca9-b042-49261b9827cc">Policies and procedures shall be established, and supporting business processes implemented, for maintaining a safe and secure working environment in offices, rooms, facilities, and secure areas storing sensitive information.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_76cece14-b5a4-4b1d-8bba-5d8457ab08c3">Can you provide evidence that policies, standards, and procedures have been established for maintaining a safe and secure working environment in offices, rooms, facilities, and secure areas?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_16014ee5-86d0-493d-bfb4-d47ce3bb3685">Can you provide evidence that your personnel and involved third parties have been trained regarding your documented policies, standards, and procedures?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_1d084269-7e38-400d-bd1d-5384683ebdbb"><title>Secure Area Authorization</title><label>DCS-07</label><description><p id="_f79334a6-13f9-4d1c-b918-f86adac96699">Ingress and egress to secure areas shall be constrained and monitored by physical access control mechanisms to ensure that only authorized personnel are allowed access.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_ab85cdee-c7db-46ed-941c-c4780cf1e8c5">Do you allow tenants to specify which of your geographic locations their data is allowed to move into/out of (to address legal jurisdictional considerations based on where data is stored vs. accessed)?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_ac791c28-d851-4018-ab84-cebeb9f786e8"><title>Unauthorized Persons Entry</title><label>DCS-08</label><description><p id="_b8418ce5-4224-40d9-ae47-37f5a2dc8ff3">Ingress and egress points such as service areas and other points where unauthorized personnel may enter the premises shall be monitored, controlled and, if possible, isolated from data storage and processing facilities to prevent unauthorized data corruption, compromise, and loss.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_a467a29a-d8cb-4e9c-9b79-af3e5417ccb1">Are ingress and egress points, such as service areas and other points where unauthorized personnel may enter the premises, monitored, controlled and isolated from data storage and process?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_c274f02c-07be-4061-a4f1-013a97f34706"><title>User Access</title><label>DCS-09</label><description><p id="_ebc35e68-99ff-4254-8247-63be055d565d">Physical access to information assets and functions by users and support personnel shall be restricted.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_543c33b3-3289-4b47-b5bb-1e8fcdf08801">Do you restrict physical access to information assets and functions by users and support personnel?</p>
</verification></requirement></requirement>
<requirement id="_7a6623e2-a665-4990-b663-8622facbead3" obligation="requirement"><title>Encryption &amp; Key Management</title><label>EKM</label><requirement id="_72efdeea-ff5e-4e7f-ac64-2d7d0fe75b65"><title>Entitlement</title><label>EKM-01</label><description><p id="_5915176d-de2b-4b93-a161-9c386c840b66">Keys must have identifiable owners (binding keys to identities) and there shall be key management policies.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_4ea2de25-9c16-4c4b-804c-19af3010bd5e">Do you have key management policies binding keys to identifiable owners?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_93618057-8895-4e5f-9e77-e5697f99db0a"><title>Key Generation</title><label>EKM-02</label><description><p id="_cf91758d-405e-4261-bdce-6d18c97ca900">Policies and procedures shall be established for the management of cryptographic keys in the service’s cryptosystem (e.g., lifecycle management from key generation to revocation and replacement, public key infrastructure, cryptographic protocol design and algorithms used, access controls in place for secure key generation, and exchange and storage including segregation of keys used for encrypted data or sessions). Upon request, provider shall inform the customer (tenant) of changes within the cryptosystem, especially if the customer (tenant) data is used as part of the service, and/or the customer (tenant) has some shared responsibility over implementation of the control.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_79be25a4-0fc5-4068-92e8-62931e94e9b3">Do you have a capability to allow creation of unique encryption keys per tenant?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_ea5253ba-ed62-430a-8245-207b3be951b5">Do you have a capability to manage encryption keys on behalf of tenants?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_5c4d7021-a339-48e5-9b77-f4c2cb9f7aa1">Do you maintain key management procedures?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_1d0e81ec-6380-4862-8b85-ed88a8bd2cc4">Do you have documented ownership for each stage of the lifecycle of encryption keys?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_9f40e7f2-e22b-48f1-97e9-bbf67d791064">Do you utilize any third party/open source/proprietary frameworks to manage encryption keys?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_63262380-c327-4bb3-b59f-1b0d530f5b5a"><title>Encryption</title><label>EKM-03</label><description><p id="_2ce8b087-3241-4cfb-93ba-6afdeebab034">Policies and procedures shall be established, and supporting business processes and technical measures implemented, for the use of encryption protocols for protection of sensitive data in storage (e.g., file servers, databases, and end-user workstations) and data in transmission (e.g., system interfaces, over public networks, and electronic messaging) as per applicable legal, statutory, and regulatory compliance obligations.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_722fbe6c-896a-4607-aaab-417811cf15c9">Do you encrypt tenant data at rest (on disk/storage) within your environment?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_6da3d97e-ab18-4511-89e5-893d4d85fdc2">Do you leverage encryption to protect data and virtual machine images during transport across and between networks and hypervisor instances?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_bd62af28-6cdc-4438-8195-e3e955cadc1b">Do you support tenant-generated encryption keys or permit tenants to encrypt data to an identity without access to a public key certificate (e.g., identity-based encryption)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_6134f4ad-254d-472e-87fc-c0c0cc713bb1">Do you have documentation establishing and defining your encryption management policies, procedures, and guidelines?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_3c081723-a239-4a9f-a2bc-39aad8f90e50"><title>Storage and Access</title><label>EKM-04</label><description><p id="_5529f174-8da8-4984-b365-e124793a1b9a">Platform and data appropriate encryption (e.g., AES-256) in open/validated formats and standard algorithms shall be required. Keys shall not be stored in the cloud (i.e. at the cloud provider in question), but maintained by the cloud consumer or trusted key management provider. Key management and key usage shall be separated duties.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_bde4269f-0dfc-4d0e-8068-4a21e36e615b">Do you have platform and data appropriate encryption that uses open/validated formats and standard algorithms?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_6d84d846-6bfc-4c02-9d5a-799bc251ad08">Are your encryption keys maintained by the cloud consumer or a trusted key management provider?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_3ba4f97a-bbca-4f7e-9525-3808cd897ada">Do you store encryption keys in the cloud?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_4c727261-86a1-4534-8f1b-2f0f2edfc062">Do you have separate key management and key usage duties?</p>
</verification></requirement></requirement>
<requirement id="_6aeeabea-73dc-4cf0-b50c-a0c1311c5913" obligation="requirement"><title>Governance and Risk Management</title><label>GRM</label><requirement id="_badef31b-f8ba-4c25-8506-52fbf0b9b888"><title>Baseline Requirements</title><label>GRM-01</label><description><p id="_3b995c3d-79f4-4ff0-bb7b-15f1276b2e6d">Baseline security requirements shall be established for developed or acquired, organizationally-owned or managed, physical or virtual, applications and infrastructure system, and network components that comply with applicable legal, statutory, and regulatory compliance obligations. Deviations from standard baseline configurations must be authorized following change management policies and procedures prior to deployment, provisioning, or use. Compliance with security baseline requirements must be reassessed at least annually unless an alternate frequency has been established and authorized based on business needs.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_68acc42f-bd16-4c27-9f3f-fdc3b2e36226">Do you have documented information security baselines for every component of your infrastructure (e.g., hypervisors, operating systems, routers, DNS servers, etc.)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_b85205dd-af17-4ba0-a3e9-1fe822a531a8">Do you have the capability to continuously monitor and report the compliance of your infrastructure against your information security baselines?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_2371d589-d603-4066-98df-cbf7fb0c065b">Do you allow your clients to provide their own trusted virtual machine image to ensure conformance to their own internal standards?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_67cd7bd5-828a-48c6-bb50-06e563b5a3ad"><title>Risk Assessments</title><label>GRM-02</label><description><p id="_e0b211a1-6876-455c-8b73-14682646065e">Risk assessments associated with data governance requirements shall be conducted at planned intervals and shall consider the following:</p>
<ul id="_205a8fb6-aa1a-42ee-bfe9-00e55a90de95">
  <li>
    <p id="_1e28d37a-ca2f-44a4-a68f-5c93d8ebb98f">Awareness of where sensitive data is stored and transmitted across applications, databases, servers, and network infrastructure</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_fc63c314-28a8-4bcd-a48a-b9228fa07b45">Compliance with defined retention periods and end-of-life disposal requirements</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_3bb7e037-3864-4edd-a45c-ebacab19bd25">Data classification and protection from unauthorized use, access, loss, destruction, and falsification</p>
  </li>
</ul>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_a28f78df-1411-4606-b39d-c1c70fb3f58b">Do you provide security control health data in order to allow tenants to implement industry standard Continuous Monitoring (which allows continual tenant validation of your physical and logical control status)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_e88a2bd2-d28b-42ad-9633-00fa72ce45ec">Do you conduct risk assessments associated with data governance requirements at least once a year?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_27b8cbff-a581-4ce7-9991-433413ba8916"><title>Management Oversight</title><label>GRM-03</label><description><p id="_e01fca91-14a5-47b3-946a-b82583390210">Managers are responsible for maintaining awareness of, and complying with, security policies, procedures, and standards that are relevant to their area of responsibility.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_5365b39c-5500-410b-8ecf-944df49ca854">Are your technical, business, and executive managers responsible for maintaining awareness of and compliance with security policies, procedures, and standards for both themselves and their employees as they pertain to the manager and employees’ area of responsibility?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_d8918b40-3b2d-4539-a283-b237fcd01c55"><title>Management Program</title><label>GRM-04</label><description><p id="_5ee80bd9-4c28-4902-ae65-32c04514c914">An Information Security Management Program (ISMP) shall be developed, documented, approved, and implemented that includes administrative, technical, and physical safeguards to protect assets and data from loss, misuse, unauthorized access, disclosure, alteration, and destruction. The security program shall include, but not be limited to, the following areas insofar as they relate to the characteristics of the business:</p>
<ul id="_abbb62da-d75f-49b5-87fe-3f2c855cd562">
  <li>
    <p id="_8e24164c-c7b3-4142-92f9-51d6275ae818">Risk management</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_5a80bfe1-05bc-4245-9f26-fb3c32f805c1">Security policy</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_2818ba3d-0294-4d9e-ad38-164b75b9d608">Organization of information security</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_4427ff18-16ec-44bd-af3d-d4aba17ab25a">Asset management</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_ec8b324c-b1f8-45ad-8efe-c50ba85a087e">Human resources security</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_c74c5702-bc2b-459a-a2a3-e4fc9c962e6f">Physical and environmental security</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_1a759c19-87c4-4398-bddf-14fe44b832f5">Communications and operations management</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_c670c854-03ec-4928-82f4-f17aadd7f02d">Access control</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_43dad2fc-8320-4691-a63a-ec669448727a">Information systems acquisition, development, and maintenance</p>
  </li>
</ul>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_40ed37ff-7c06-4e97-bfb6-3ce0615fab81">Do you provide tenants with documentation describing your Information Security Management Program (ISMP)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_55351546-9fa7-42b4-be86-86ed1e3bfb53">Do you review your Information Security Management Program (ISMP) at least once a year?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_d5c54d79-2251-45c8-ad15-b438f6bf4aa8"><title>Management Support / Involvement</title><label>GRM-05</label><description><p id="_6b62d67f-9a3d-4152-9fce-91d9de7d9c02">Executive and line management shall take formal action to support information security through clearly-documented direction and commitment, and shall ensure the action has been assigned.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_0d29073a-fc44-4eba-9462-41daf2e8d410">Do you ensure your providers adhere to your information security and privacy policies?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_aab47eff-d16c-41f5-a982-639c57ee75e5"><title>Policy</title><label>GRM-06</label><description><p id="_5d99c875-53a0-4990-86f4-36b3e1860103">Information security policies and procedures shall be established and made readily available for review by all impacted personnel and external business relationships. Information security policies must be authorized by the organization’s business leadership (or other accountable business role or function) and supported by a strategic business plan and an information security management program inclusive of defined information security roles and responsibilities for business leadership.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_23ee8982-3124-4c64-a900-ea5ef1073c5c">Do your information security and privacy policies align with industry standards (ISO-27001, ISO-22307, CoBIT, etc.)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_7fb387ed-4ad3-4889-ba13-69d9fa14e890">Do you have agreements to ensure your providers adhere to your information security and privacy policies?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_4314f625-b444-4d9c-a93b-8b459393e8ea">Can you provide evidence of due diligence mapping of your controls, architecture, and processes to regulations and/or standards?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_1ed02317-54c8-40b6-967e-4071c22bd128">Do you disclose which controls, standards, certifications, and/or regulations you comply with?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_d7387800-7691-430a-ae0f-a3c65f47c222"><title>Policy Enforcement</title><label>GRM-07</label><description><p id="_ab103166-4c25-449d-96b8-ee330559623d">A formal disciplinary or sanction policy shall be established for employees who have violated security policies and procedures. Employees shall be made aware of what action might be taken in the event of a violation, and disciplinary measures must be stated in the policies and procedures.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_b9f4e774-6562-4883-9614-adb5c38fa94d">Is a formal disciplinary or sanction policy established for employees who have violated security policies and procedures?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_63f714f6-0906-4f5f-a6b9-707bbe7e0c4a">Are employees made aware of what actions could be taken in the event of a violation via their policies and procedures?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_c57aea3b-791b-44c4-8698-6b5eed84ce59"><title>Business / Policy Change Impacts</title><label>GRM-08</label><description><p id="_1d41d825-d4d2-4924-935c-6479d606cc39">Risk assessment results shall include updates to security policies, procedures, standards, and controls to ensure that they remain relevant and effective.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_6ba3aeea-e82f-4a63-b181-68dda623bee6">Do risk assessment results include updates to security policies, procedures, standards, and controls to ensure they remain relevant and effective?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_e8c49550-40cb-4042-abe7-28c716ebeb86"><title>Policy Reviews</title><label>GRM-09</label><description><p id="_fc84eba6-dd87-4cc6-a6c5-b77d85024764">The organization’s business leadership (or other accountable business role or function) shall review the information security policy at planned intervals or as a result of changes to the organization to ensure its continuing alignment with the security strategy, effectiveness, accuracy, relevance, and applicability to legal, statutory, or regulatory compliance obligations.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_60e4bd34-30a3-4c8f-8619-09aaccc3c134">Do you notify your tenants when you make material changes to your information security and/or privacy policies?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_3e11e277-b1c8-4043-9b82-49410c37c6d5">Do you perform, at minimum, annual reviews to your privacy and security policies?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_cfa57d69-7aa2-43fa-bbda-38d187f0f5f1"><title>Assessments</title><label>GRM-10</label><description><p id="_947c2b51-e2ce-4ec0-b0b8-1daeda88476d">Aligned with the enterprise-wide framework, formal risk assessments shall be performed at least annually or at planned intervals, (and in conjunction with any changes to information systems) to determine the likelihood and impact of all identified risks using qualitative and quantitative methods. The likelihood and impact associated with inherent and residual risk shall be determined independently, considering all risk categories (e.g., audit results, threat and vulnerability analysis, and regulatory compliance).</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_e0f0cc7e-67dc-4ed8-a913-c7bca19d944e">Are formal risk assessments aligned with the enterprise-wide framework and performed at least annually, or at planned intervals, determining the likelihood and impact of all identified risks, using qualitative and quantitative methods?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_2994df44-32ae-4285-a34a-f797c8cd6e96">Is the likelihood and impact associated with inherent and residual risk determined independently, considering all risk categories (e.g., audit results, threat and vulnerability analysis, and regulatory compliance)?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_04b2b323-4222-42df-b87d-bdc5c4cb3677"><title>Program</title><label>GRM-11</label><description><p id="_d81318d5-134d-4e92-9462-34c1a22f5986">Risks shall be mitigated to an acceptable level. Acceptance levels based on risk criteria shall be established and documented in accordance with reasonable resolution time frames and stakeholder approval.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_ef5993de-564f-4ca2-af8c-1394810bf3d8">Do you have a documented, organization-wide program in place to manage risk?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_a1a5bae6-38d5-4e8c-b62b-04c1d7470df5">Do you make available documentation of your organization-wide risk management program?</p>
</verification></requirement></requirement>
<requirement id="_32dc27a9-f013-414e-8898-0bce5590cc3d" obligation="requirement"><title>Human Resources</title><label>HRS</label><requirement id="_52574439-ea94-4e7a-9ab8-bd99cf173c27"><title>Asset Returns</title><label>HRS-01</label><description><p id="_66f5cb71-9e8f-4be9-a56b-e5f189f1ea63">Upon termination of workforce personnel and/or expiration of external business relationships, all organizationally-owned assets shall be returned within an established period.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_e01c0aab-78d7-427c-8f8d-0187993a0152">Are systems in place to monitor for privacy breaches and notify tenants expeditiously if a privacy event may have impacted their data?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_ea8de7a9-fd82-42db-9d16-835cb2b9ffcf">Is your Privacy Policy aligned with industry standards?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_e1963cda-de58-4af2-aa98-42d047d03883"><title>Background Screening</title><label>HRS-02</label><description><p id="_8f5b7df0-39c2-4c47-b396-3a34c0dbe57e">Pursuant to local laws, regulations, ethics, and contractual constraints, all employment candidates, contractors, and third parties shall be subject to background verification proportional to the data classification to be accessed, the business requirements, and acceptable risk.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_f9619332-3a35-400a-b9a0-47eee27fe4aa">Pursuant to local laws, regulations, ethics, and contractual constraints, are all employment candidates, contractors, and involved third parties subject to background verification?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_7e01a55d-e586-4124-af99-30933532626c"><title>Employment Agreements</title><label>HRS-03</label><description><p id="_a05b8ff7-7b6f-49e5-bcd6-b78349cd18ca">Employment agreements shall incorporate provisions and/or terms for adherence to established information governance and security policies and must be signed by newly hired or on-boarded workforce personnel (e.g., full or part-time employee or contingent staff) prior to granting workforce personnel user access to corporate facilities, resources, and assets.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_d9117143-1230-4a16-9cc9-d3665632a22c">Do you specifically train your employees regarding their specific role and the information security controls they must fulfill?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_82d341b9-2ac6-4986-8825-b9336a9210d7">Do you document employee acknowledgment of training they have completed?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_6127921f-cb9f-45ab-a039-8d19c3b27c03">Are all personnel required to sign NDA or Confidentiality Agreements as a condition of employment to protect customer/tenant information?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_ebf225c5-3b32-48cd-aa6c-b1ec7ff30c07">Is successful and timed completion of the training program considered a prerequisite for acquiring and maintaining access to sensitive systems?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_f51bf55b-c7e2-4275-a350-5dd1727b577d">Are personnel trained and provided with awareness programs at least once a year?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_c058323b-85ad-42e1-b2fb-2edb995a5cda"><title>Employment Termination</title><label>HRS-04</label><description><p id="_e2fa2c35-d033-422b-afe4-d20befef0c30">Roles and responsibilities for performing employment termination or change in employment procedures shall be assigned, documented, and communicated.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_b3d2c9fc-cb9e-468e-a07b-daf3eab60fa4">Are documented policies, procedures, and guidelines in place to govern change in employment and/or termination?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_4582587d-8b09-4b3b-9125-e3d3d5f4ff50">Do the above procedures and guidelines account for timely revocation of access and return of assets?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_a45fa227-7d53-409d-8c78-e924b982699c"><title>Portable / Mobile Devices</title><label>HRS-05</label><description><p id="_8e5e1c66-8ec1-4bdb-ae55-dfeec15e2339">Policies and procedures shall be established, and supporting business processes and technical measures implemented, to manage business risks associated with permitting mobile device access to corporate resources and may require the implementation of higher assurance compensating controls and acceptable-use policies and procedures (e.g., mandated security training, stronger identity, entitlement and access controls, and device monitoring).</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_31b57a46-8d61-4591-970b-139b516bcff8">Are policies and procedures established and measures implemented to strictly limit access to your sensitive data and tenant data from portable and mobile devices (e.g., laptops, cell phones, and personal digital assistants (PDAs)), which are generally higher-risk than non-portable devices (e.g., desktop computers at the provider organization’s facilities)?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_61a015e2-6ebc-4216-affc-17529f69004b"><title>Non-Disclosure Agreements</title><label>HRS-06</label><description><p id="_4f605724-b9f8-4954-99ba-3c26f7b2a021">Requirements for non-disclosure or confidentiality agreements reflecting the organization’s needs for the protection of data and operational details shall be identified, documented, and reviewed at planned intervals.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_4f8a9c69-f745-44da-a13d-22a1a4c8e223">Are requirements for non-disclosure or confidentiality agreements reflecting the organization’s needs for the protection of data and operational details identified, documented, and reviewed at planned intervals?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_8cd83f59-e794-4dca-85fa-e3aba7546ba8"><title>Roles / Responsibilities</title><label>HRS-07</label><description><p id="_a81989dc-73d4-4274-aed2-9dc75167596a">Roles and responsibilities of contractors, employees, and third-party users shall be documented as they relate to information assets and security.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_394a12b9-9fe3-4abb-9de2-ac910735355e">Do you provide tenants with a role definition document clarifying your administrative responsibilities versus those of the tenant?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_20c81283-b23c-4fe5-84c3-0bbe87808453"><title>Acceptable Use</title><label>HRS-08</label><description><p id="_22a4298f-1243-408d-a42d-625b817bbe71">Policies and procedures shall be established, and supporting business processes and technical measures implemented, for defining allowances and conditions for permitting usage of organizationally-owned or managed user end-point devices (e.g., issued workstations, laptops, and mobile devices) and IT infrastructure network and systems components. Additionally, defining allowances and conditions to permit usage of personal mobile devices and associated applications with access to corporate resources (i.e., BYOD) shall be considered and incorporated as appropriate.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_20316194-3ee5-4b33-9283-89a166f44359">Do you provide documentation regarding how you may access tenant data and metadata?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_cf700b05-94f3-4640-8f66-d23b7d4f9b44">Do you collect or create metadata about tenant data usage through inspection technologies (e.g., search engines, etc.)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_741f1610-9f87-49b1-be8e-aadd51a6a243">Do you allow tenants to opt out of having their data/metadata accessed via inspection technologies?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_7780adf6-dd0f-4a2b-82a8-b05e1636ef3c"><title>Training / Awareness</title><label>HRS-09</label><description><p id="_2b1b0a3b-e834-4ce6-8590-ed4da9849117">A security awareness training program shall be established for all contractors, third-party users, and employees of the organization and mandated when appropriate. All individuals with access to organizational data shall receive appropriate awareness training and regular updates in organizational procedures, processes, and policies relating to their professional function relative to the organization.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_04e440dd-8671-4f57-bd64-7734413b60db">Do you provide a formal, role-based, security awareness training program for cloud-related access and data management issues (e.g., multi-tenancy, nationality, cloud delivery model, segregation of duties implications, and conflicts of interest) for all persons with access to tenant data?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_28ea8ae0-c188-411e-b672-3c374eee219e">Are administrators and data stewards properly educated on their legal responsibilities with regard to security and data integrity?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_d3582816-841f-4f57-b87c-abe54d3b7d15"><title>User Responsibility</title><label>HRS-10</label><description><p id="_a04af5f8-59d9-42c5-a3d9-233300057ae3">All personnel shall be made aware of their roles and responsibilities for:</p>
<ul id="_546aac0c-f20c-4ded-9519-0b7c681de829">
  <li>
    <p id="_229ee6f8-11d3-42b6-9f3a-350d766ad05b">Maintaining awareness and compliance with established policies and procedures and applicable legal, statutory, or regulatory compliance obligations.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_4f8d5982-5fcf-469c-b474-0cb95355188d">Maintaining a safe and secure working environment</p>
  </li>
</ul>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_b85e28c8-4f2d-443c-9ea0-70332aed9783">Are users made aware of their responsibilities for maintaining awareness and compliance with published security policies, procedures, standards, and applicable regulatory requirements?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_b7af40b1-92ea-4877-bf56-0db388c4485b">Are users made aware of their responsibilities for maintaining a safe and secure working environment?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_9a9bcb77-171f-4ac7-8bd1-0e0da2da006a">Are users made aware of their responsibilities for leaving unattended equipment in a secure manner?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_0723a6d2-79ea-4f30-a2e4-9f23e7cf583f"><title>Workspace</title><label>HRS-11</label><description><p id="_996e8816-04cc-43b4-bbda-afbbf8b82041">Policies and procedures shall be established to require that unattended workspaces do not have openly visible (e.g., on a desktop) sensitive documents and user computing sessions had been disabled after an established period of inactivity.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_27aeaf01-09ae-4a14-92ae-8a5b9e02a84d">Do your data management policies and procedures address tenant and service level conflicts of interests?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_4a0cf095-2ca5-420f-a3d4-55f1f9191b88">Do your data management policies and procedures include a tamper audit or software integrity function for unauthorized access to tenant data?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_66ff2287-c8d3-4e71-a311-f7f8d94b23b6">Does the virtual machine management infrastructure include a tamper audit or software integrity function to detect changes to the build/configuration of the virtual machine?</p>
</verification></requirement></requirement>
<requirement id="_327e881f-e8f6-42fd-b0b3-2fd6999b567f" obligation="requirement"><title>Identity &amp; Access Management</title><label>IAM</label><requirement id="_1b25b022-697c-4765-8a01-720a270b21d0"><title>Audit Tools Access</title><label>IAM-01</label><description><p id="_8b13cc5e-f427-4d7e-92a9-112060e599bf">Access to, and use of, audit tools that interact with the organization’s information systems shall be appropriately segmented and restricted to prevent compromise and misuse of log data.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_82e63b39-ce4d-44f8-b20a-388a672e3a4a">Do you restrict, log, and monitor access to your information security management systems (e.g., hypervisors, firewalls, vulnerability scanners, network sniffers, APIs, etc.)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_20c54021-47b5-4952-be32-ae52e5bf7316">Do you monitor and log privileged access (e.g., administrator level) to information security management systems?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_e104dbe5-6216-45b4-b07d-57ff85307481"><title>User Access Policy</title><label>IAM-02</label><description><p id="_48d1d07d-a9ce-440c-8d28-e8d801794a8b">User access policies and procedures shall be established, and supporting business processes and technical measures implemented, for ensuring appropriate identity, entitlement, and access management for all internal corporate and customer (tenant) users with access to data and organizationally-owned or managed (physical and virtual) application interfaces and infrastructure network and systems components. These policies, procedures, processes, and measures must incorporate the following:</p>
<ul id="_29fa86a1-f47a-4623-aa1d-7bb4a8ced5b5">
  <li>
    <p id="_8e02c212-70da-4533-bf62-c7b9f1a81d3b">Procedures, supporting roles, and responsibilities for provisioning and de-provisioning user account entitlements following the rule of least privilege based on job function (e.g., internal employee and contingent staff personnel changes, customer-controlled access, suppliers’ business relationships, or other third-party business relationships)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_6670157a-61dd-4f97-97b6-61fe4f3d5130">Business case considerations for higher levels of assurance and multi-factor authentication secrets (e.g., management interfaces, key generation, remote access, segregation of duties, emergency access, large-scale provisioning or geographically-distributed deployments, and personnel redundancy for critical systems)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_0da557d3-c8ff-481c-8de4-2d1336fffce1">Access segmentation to sessions and data in multi-tenant architectures by any third party (e.g., provider and/or other customer (tenant))</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_28175dfb-e502-499d-b61e-cb9832e1edeb">Identity trust verification and service-to-service application (API) and information processing interoperability (e.g., SSO and federation)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_729ebdda-eafa-4bb3-ad62-cde262ff771c">Account credential lifecycle management from instantiation through revocation</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_0cf1c3d9-7d68-44c5-a8fd-11abeed37acb">Account credential and/or identity store minimization or re-use when feasible</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_9452b8c0-33ae-4de4-89a3-022af31e9546">Authentication, authorization, and accounting (AAA) rules for access to data and sessions (e.g., encryption and strong/multi-factor, expireable, non-shared authentication secrets)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_d52d3cc1-1002-4edd-b7bb-9e214a10ead1">Permissions and supporting capabilities for customer (tenant) controls over authentication, authorization, and accounting (AAA) rules for access to data and sessions</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_6af71632-98e7-4efa-a8cd-20e1d8b0e41e">Adherence to applicable legal, statutory, or regulatory compliance requirements</p>
  </li>
</ul>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_aac2ba19-b541-44b9-a32d-42e2943447ba">Do you have controls in place ensuring timely removal of systems access that is no longer required for business purposes?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_a587441c-1147-44bd-81c1-72b6a899c213">Do you provide metrics to track the speed with which you are able to remove systems access that is no longer required for business purposes?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_adb9d0b3-8c32-49ef-a323-c2a0ce9cc2fe"><title>Diagnostic / Configuration Ports Access</title><label>IAM-03</label><description><p id="_23e7f8e3-a175-4b78-bb26-5a88fb20b631">User access to diagnostic and configuration ports shall be restricted to authorized individuals and applications.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_c4179553-336e-4193-b213-e864a4dc5eea">Do you use dedicated secure networks to provide management access to your cloud service infrastructure?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_3bd2a706-d4bc-43f4-8faa-955c9ea7eef4"><title>Policies and Procedures</title><label>IAM-04</label><description><p id="_84de2b9a-bf69-4b29-8515-1da7ab963197">Policies and procedures shall be established to store and manage identity information about every person who accesses IT infrastructure and to determine their level of access. Policies shall also be developed to control access to network resources based on user identity.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_6c281ed4-f7c4-4785-8f7b-70dc9782c7e5">Do you manage and store the identity of all personnel who have access to the IT infrastructure, including their level of access?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_6b3ca6db-7abd-4e9b-ae95-bf07c57eeedb">Do you manage and store the user identity of all personnel who have network access, including their level of access?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_c38aa02f-d882-4553-b669-3c6496a817e7"><title>Segregation of Duties</title><label>IAM-05</label><description><p id="_4a319a24-aa4d-4bd9-a6b9-2616c7cecac5">User access policies and procedures shall be established, and supporting business processes and technical measures implemented, for restricting user access as per defined segregation of duties to address business risks associated with a user-role conflict of interest.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_9269adf2-85f3-4c67-8405-b8f35fff966b">Do you provide tenants with documentation on how you maintain segregation of duties within your cloud service offering?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_f674d9d9-e961-4f0d-a42e-4a1bc9b0d6ee"><title>Source Code Access Restriction</title><label>IAM-06</label><description><p id="_f36248b6-112e-4bff-ba35-783b1e3ef60f">Access to the organization’s own developed applications, program, or object source code, or any other form of intellectual property (IP), and use of proprietary software shall be appropriately restricted following the rule of least privilege based on job function as per established user access policies and procedures.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_2ebbc8c4-1699-47dd-87f2-6d88659f224c">Are controls in place to prevent unauthorized access to your application, program, or object source code, and assure it is restricted to authorized personnel only?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_f2e146a3-16e9-47b7-be13-cda4e68e6a36">Are controls in place to prevent unauthorized access to tenant application, program, or object source code, and assure it is restricted to authorized personnel only?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_114b711d-dd7a-4565-b456-ca7e60e63edf"><title>Third Party Access</title><label>IAM-07</label><description><p id="_dfe4790e-a88e-4720-9c5f-6195f829249e">The identification, assessment, and prioritization of risks posed by business processes requiring third-party access to the organization’s information systems and data shall be followed by coordinated application of resources to minimize, monitor, and measure likelihood and impact of unauthorized or inappropriate access. Compensating controls derived from the risk analysis shall be implemented prior to provisioning access.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_73a22881-351a-4d4f-90bb-f7eba0681be3">Do you provide multi-failure disaster recovery capability?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_0cd5ce92-05c4-4045-aed0-84bac61f1722">Do you monitor service continuity with upstream providers in the event of provider failure?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_50629c33-9618-447b-8225-2a3a73d32099">Do you have more than one provider for each service you depend on?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_83b92ab8-5583-428f-bda1-0185b2ef4314">Do you provide access to operational redundancy and continuity summaries, including the services you depend on?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_d845c92c-aaa3-4926-9450-e8e09db4f48f">Do you provide the tenant the ability to declare a disaster?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_b6e83a96-4b0d-4d6a-b305-07bdd811a606">Do you provide a tenant-triggered failover option?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_45114a97-6c51-4162-b61d-b7df2a4b4e15">Do you share your business continuity and redundancy plans with your tenants?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_576d86a7-e072-4d54-b5bb-7048a8a7e77a"><title>User Access Restriction / Authorization</title><label>IAM-08</label><description><p id="_768990ad-a3e6-4c49-b1fe-65c31a2ecdf2">Policies and procedures are established for permissible storage and access of identities used for authentication to ensure identities are only accessible based on rules of least privilege and replication limitation only to users explicitly defined as business necessary.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_a347287e-ca88-4d1b-bd93-689482588b79">Do you document how you grant and approve access to tenant data?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_f4fb21a0-ee93-436a-9224-cb445517bf7d">Do you have a method of aligning provider and tenant data classification methodologies for access control purposes?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_e43902ac-223a-487b-9582-0c4202624073"><title>User Access Authorization</title><label>IAM-09</label><description><p id="_dc19f290-e50c-4050-a169-e368ffaf221e">Provisioning user access (e.g., employees, contractors, customers (tenants), business partners and/or supplier relationships) to data and organizationally-owned or managed (physical and virtual) applications, infrastructure systems, and network components shall be authorized by the organization’s management prior to access being granted and appropriately restricted as per established policies and procedures. Upon request, provider shall inform customer (tenant) of this user access, especially if customer (tenant) data is used as part of the service and/or customer (tenant) has some shared responsibility over implementation of control.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_749067d5-7df2-436d-8604-e2351f1ac4d7">Does your management provision the authorization and restrictions for user access (e.g., employees, contractors, customers (tenants), business partners, and/or suppliers) prior to their access to data and any owned or managed (physical and virtual) applications, infrastructure systems, and network components?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_abda6963-8ad9-43ef-abb5-7a346b5d681c">Do you provide upon request user access (e.g., employees, contractors, customers (tenants), business partners and/or suppliers) to data and any owned or managed (physical and virtual) applications, infrastructure systems and network components?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_725397cb-c459-4293-8dc5-3e933ce53207"><title>User Access Reviews</title><label>IAM-10</label><description><p id="_a2b46e64-6012-4ea5-a73f-da61e1b119a0">User access shall be authorized and revalidated for entitlement appropriateness, at planned intervals, by the organization’s business leadership or other accountable business role or function supported by evidence to demonstrate the organization is adhering to the rule of least privilege based on job function. For identified access violations, remediation must follow established user access policies and procedures.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_e62ad5ec-bc06-43bc-8361-cc5502b8f4e4">Do you require at least annual certification of entitlements for all system users and administrators (exclusive of users maintained by your tenants)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_8637c46c-7652-46b3-8056-b314abf2cb3d">If users are found to have inappropriate entitlements, are all remediation and certification actions recorded?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_2d513b19-26e6-47d1-8105-0e4517cfeeb3">Will you share user entitlement remediation and certification reports with your tenants, if inappropriate access may have been allowed to tenant data?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_2be840d4-53a3-44bf-922a-9aad37141bd6"><title>User Access Revocation</title><label>IAM-11</label><description><p id="_34cde40e-893c-4b3c-bea5-874155e510ef">Timely de-provisioning (revocation or modification) of user access to data and organizationally-owned or managed (physical and virtual) applications, infrastructure systems, and network components, shall be implemented as per established policies and procedures and based on user’s change in status (e.g., termination of employment or other business relationship, job change, or transfer). Upon request, provider shall inform customer (tenant) of these changes, especially if customer (tenant) data is used as part the service and/or customer (tenant) has some shared responsibility over implementation of control.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_18daeaad-1cd3-4371-af90-c05d0c586472">Is timely deprovisioning, revocation, or modification of user access to the organizations systems, information assets, and data implemented upon any change in status of employees, contractors, customers, business partners, or involved third parties?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_a8ace5b0-838b-4d7d-af62-86489ba4ff72">Is any change in user access status intended to include termination of employment, contract or agreement, change of employment or transfer within the organization?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_43961b77-11dc-4c4b-b51e-560864a51b1a"><title>User ID Credentials</title><label>IAM-12</label><description><p id="_8f9f58cf-6b6a-4123-9987-b4976509be90">Internal corporate or customer (tenant) user account credentials shall be restricted as per the following, ensuring appropriate identity, entitlement, and access management and in accordance with established policies and procedures:</p>
<ul id="_690fa178-b38e-4590-9e0e-af1a4a60becf">
  <li>
    <p id="_b6bb1309-901b-4eae-87de-d106a620a4b6">Identity trust verification and service-to-service application (API) and information processing interoperability (e.g., SSO and Federation)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_58d65bfd-cd73-4405-9c6a-2af8a56e9780">Account credential lifecycle management from instantiation through revocation</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_a26cf88f-f7e9-4e44-9637-5317a5aac7c3">Account credential and/or identity store minimization or re-use when feasible</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_45b76721-87ae-457d-adb0-76d3a75f2b3f">Adherence to industry acceptable and/or regulatory compliant authentication, authorization, and accounting (AAA) rules (e.g., strong/multi-factor, expireable, non-shared authentication secrets)</p>
  </li>
</ul>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_8e48023c-8ae4-415f-82fd-b29b074f7289">Do you support use of, or integration with, existing customer-based Single Sign On (SSO) solutions to your service?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_fe1bb2f3-2a5f-475a-b22b-f68fe5be90d7">Do you use open standards to delegate authentication capabilities to your tenants?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_f9e89796-ce87-42f0-a35c-23009c640371">Do you support identity federation standards (e.g., SAML, SPML, WS-Federation, etc.) as a means of authenticating/authorizing users?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_3ad47c7a-2553-4660-a8ed-3e6d93bb0917">Do you have a Policy Enforcement Point capability (e.g., XACML) to enforce regional legal and policy constraints on user access?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_59652ad2-fe3c-4bdb-8a95-31d54becdbf7">Do you have an identity management system (enabling classification of data for a tenant) in place to enable both role-based and context-based entitlement to data?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_d33c0cf2-503d-4d90-ae8f-5989f2e88a18">Do you provide tenants with strong (multifactor) authentication options (e.g., digital certs, tokens, biometrics, etc.) for user access?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_c579fce0-81b4-497e-9805-9d2176fd783d">Do you allow tenants to use third-party identity assurance services?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_378c9766-8c61-4b5f-a09d-a4233b58fe9a">Do you support password (e.g., minimum length, age, history, complexity) and account lockout (e.g., lockout threshold, lockout duration) policy enforcement?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_7ca0bd10-d1da-492f-a7e9-d887b3726fc5">Do you allow tenants/customers to define password and account lockout policies for their accounts?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_6e6494b5-76c9-4dd4-9f11-22b8447ae9f6">Do you support the ability to force password changes upon first logon?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_8558b5a4-4425-49e0-bbe2-54199812ac0d">Do you have mechanisms in place for unlocking accounts that have been locked out (e.g., self-service via email, defined challenge questions, manual unlock)?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_c3107613-552f-4d9f-8386-03ec64bee152"><title>Utility Programs Access</title><label>IAM-13</label><description><p id="_f7453508-e42e-4c4e-92fe-49d3df1ee6ec">Utility programs capable of potentially overriding system, object, network, virtual machine, and application controls shall be restricted.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_b4f96b8f-b71b-4082-8f16-86c06b645178">Are utilities that can significantly manage virtualized partitions (e.g., shutdown, clone, etc.) appropriately restricted and monitored?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_647f621b-ad2d-4aca-ba9f-0d4b559bcb53">Do you have the capability to detect attacks that target the virtual infrastructure directly (e.g., shimming, Blue Pill, Hyper jumping, etc.)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_71716cbf-7975-4234-99d4-13d8e180d1d1">Are attacks that target the virtual infrastructure prevented with technical controls?</p>
</verification></requirement></requirement>
<requirement id="_bbe69d68-4e81-439e-8bac-7233c77d40b5" obligation="requirement"><title>Infrastructure &amp; Virtualization Security</title><label>IVS</label><requirement id="_59d2c8c2-f256-4c26-a6fb-7d8ddf031a35"><title>Audit Logging / Intrusion Detection</title><label>IVS-01</label><description><p id="_6dd6841a-8440-460a-b9d3-5eda0e84e79c">Higher levels of assurance are required for protection, retention, and lifecycle management of audit logs, adhering to applicable legal, statutory, or regulatory compliance obligations and providing unique user access accountability to detect potentially suspicious network behaviors and/or file integrity anomalies, and to support forensic investigative capabilities in the event of a security breach.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_79e42137-ff5f-47a6-9044-72b7529dace1">Are file integrity (host) and network intrusion detection (IDS) tools implemented to help facilitate timely detection, investigation by root cause analysis, and response to incidents?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_00cc345e-3a97-45b3-8846-42a8e3d9f36a">Is physical and logical user access to audit logs restricted to authorized personnel?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_0ad500a0-953c-421f-87cc-8a16a05d6af2">Can you provide evidence that due diligence mapping of regulations and standards to your controls/architecture/processes has been done?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_6a14c311-b019-4ed5-b16f-4ebd267fbcf0">Are audit logs centrally stored and retained?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_68ce052e-c6df-4ebf-98ab-985aa9ca3a1d">Are audit logs reviewed on a regular basis for security events (e.g., with automated tools)?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_76cac439-4e08-4306-a3cb-7e352d8a81ae"><title>Change Detection</title><label>IVS-02</label><description><p id="_3f9e10c0-3cc9-4331-ae23-30a7819e471b">The provider shall ensure the integrity of all virtual machine images at all times. Any changes made to virtual machine images must be logged and an alert raised regardless of their running state (e.g., dormant, off, or running). The results of a change or move of an image and the subsequent validation of the image’s integrity must be immediately available to customers through electronic methods (e.g., portals or alerts).</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_d3a47e51-69d7-4c06-8285-4f2b452967b3">Do you log and alert any changes made to virtual machine images regardless of their running state (e.g., dormant, off or running)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_a4ec34c4-ae7b-43dd-bf3a-38a01e2ada0e">Are changes made to virtual machines, or moving of an image and subsequent validation of the image’s integrity, made immediately available to customers through electronic methods (e.g., portals or alerts)?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_063aaaf9-5584-410c-8455-d98e838a2a4c"><title>Clock Synchronization</title><label>IVS-03</label><description><p id="_f7ab4a10-e938-4570-8802-f6ede9385123">A reliable and mutually agreed upon external time source shall be used to synchronize the system clocks of all relevant information processing systems to facilitate tracing and reconstitution of activity timelines.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_d61beb36-340b-4dbf-81a9-98e4921e1093">Do you use a synchronized time-service protocol (e.g., NTP) to ensure all systems have a common time reference?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_579b86e3-0bde-4dde-9407-e9ac2690fab1"><title>Capacity / Resource Planning</title><label>IVS-04</label><description><p id="_aaaba5a8-a07b-4c1c-91f8-e58b0287c202">The availability, quality, and adequate capacity and resources shall be planned, prepared, and measured to deliver the required system performance in accordance with legal, statutory, and regulatory compliance obligations. Projections of future capacity requirements shall be made to mitigate the risk of system overload.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_53e91c05-db2d-4d3a-9c68-52b942749a0b">Do you provide documentation regarding what levels of system (e.g., network, storage, memory, I/O, etc.) oversubscription you maintain and under what circumstances/scenarios?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_c7be130d-78c2-4449-9c6e-0afc5a0ac890">Do you restrict use of the memory oversubscription capabilities present in the hypervisor?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_4951fb4d-0217-4ecb-999b-8f83f0a3e766">Do your system capacity requirements take into account current, projected, and anticipated capacity needs for all systems used to provide services to the tenants?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_ce2eec39-67b1-4461-a192-8bfdd5b8c0c3">Is system performance monitored and tuned in order to continuously meet regulatory, contractual, and business requirements for all the systems used to provide services to the tenants?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_dda36637-ffd2-44ad-a3ad-5342420370be"><title>Management - Vulnerability Management</title><label>IVS-05</label><description><p id="_327a8181-bc81-4c51-aded-1a38be3c003e">Implementers shall ensure that the security vulnerability assessment tools or services accommodate the virtualization technologies used (e.g., virtualization aware).</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_c6b6a68a-ebac-4f40-814b-bb408abf2244">Do security vulnerability assessment tools or services accommodate the virtualization technologies being used (e.g., virtualization aware)?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_1728d9e1-3465-4000-83c3-056e8a554882"><title>Network Security</title><label>IVS-06</label><description><p id="_a02c7890-4401-4d7c-b1d2-c7df7fd20602">Network environments and virtual instances shall be designed and configured to restrict and monitor traffic between trusted and untrusted connections. These configurations shall be reviewed at least annually, and supported by a documented justification for use for all allowed services, protocols, ports, and compensating controls.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_4833f633-6222-4089-9f8e-fe4d7e330b1f">For your IaaS offering, do you provide customers with guidance on how to create a layered security architecture equivalence using your virtualized solution?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_f7ed24ba-62c8-4edd-8d8a-d2e7d8e195f6">Do you regularly update network architecture diagrams that include data flows between security domains/zones?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_ff6b12bf-850e-4e75-87c3-abb2ff17c6c4">Do you regularly review for appropriateness the allowed access/connectivity (e.g., firewall rules) between security domains/zones within the network?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_1847d9b9-0c07-46e1-b82d-8b2b4fad224b">Are all firewall access control lists documented with business justification?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_753126aa-0d66-4097-bc19-7a0583ceed8a"><title>OS Hardening and Base Controls</title><label>IVS-07</label><description><p id="_7ae2ad7d-42ec-4be0-90b0-445e504118d8">Each operating system shall be hardened to provide only necessary ports, protocols, and services to meet business needs and have in place supporting technical controls such as: antivirus, file integrity monitoring, and logging as part of their baseline operating build standard or template.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_c65eaa93-b39b-4faf-bf4f-48f1fc0da103">Are operating systems hardened to provide only the necessary ports, protocols, and services to meet business needs using technical controls (e.g., antivirus, file integrity monitoring, and logging) as part of their baseline build standard or template?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_8d947cc6-d7fb-4c58-aeb4-39ccbc342a47"><title>Production / Non-Production Environments</title><label>IVS-08</label><description><p id="_4d92e6df-6a1b-477b-8733-f8292d58560d">Production and non-production environments shall be separated to prevent unauthorized access or changes to information assets. Separation of the environments may include: stateful inspection firewalls, domain/realm authentication sources, and clear segregation of duties for personnel accessing these environments as part of their job duties.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_f69e8776-05b2-46ae-b99e-d0e7c01c9ce7">For your SaaS or PaaS offering, do you provide tenants with separate environments for production and test processes?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_89a59f92-3ae5-4472-b76a-71ea92a72d6c">For your IaaS offering, do you provide tenants with guidance on how to create suitable production and test environments?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_00ba3066-5c50-474c-8322-216e87bf32c2">Do you logically and physically segregate production and non-production environments?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_4472d838-cb94-48f0-8a82-365af032e852"><title>Segmentation</title><label>IVS-09</label><description><p id="_7c4c7a8a-f160-4f8e-bc78-41319173e12c">Multi-tenant organizationally-owned or managed (physical and virtual) applications, and infrastructure system and network components, shall be designed, developed, deployed, and configured such that provider and customer (tenant) user access is appropriately segmented from other tenant users, based on the following considerations:</p>
<ul id="_626c23f1-3ae5-4595-8e65-e5c770abd055">
  <li>
    <p id="_379780de-2154-44d3-a22f-36220e34e347">Established policies and procedures</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_a33531ed-d552-457a-9417-8ef24ef10493">Isolation of business critical assets and/or sensitive user data and sessions that mandate stronger internal controls and high levels of assurance</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_49b991f7-6178-4d35-833d-b8caac0f32e7">Compliance with legal, statutory, and regulatory compliance obligations</p>
  </li>
</ul>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_695196bb-60db-4a46-9405-ea53b95da6d9">Are system and network environments protected by a firewall or virtual firewall to ensure business and customer security requirements?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_c13c3da9-587f-4e3c-b0a3-72277d47c089">Are system and network environments protected by a firewall or virtual firewall to ensure compliance with legislative, regulatory, and contractual requirements?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_5ea9007d-7eed-457b-af26-a3904ad45e1f">Are system and network environments protected by a firewall or virtual firewall to ensure separation of production and non-production environments?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_5efa1ca3-699d-44d3-ad58-f1ec0395023a">Are system and network environments protected by a firewall or virtual firewall to ensure protection and isolation of sensitive data?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_9dc85cd4-67a7-4ec4-9681-4439a0488907"><title>VM Security - Data Protection</title><label>IVS-10</label><description><p id="_2d97bbb0-c48e-4101-b158-0775fb96c0f3">Secured and encrypted communication channels shall be used when migrating physical servers, applications, or data to virtualized servers and, where possible, shall use a network segregated from production-level networks for such migrations.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_c19aca14-cfc2-4d4b-84f8-d6f1c55bf8b8">Are secured and encrypted communication channels used when migrating physical servers, applications, or data to virtual servers?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_df6f89b7-5bac-4871-962b-6ef4a2a637b2">Do you use a network segregated from production-level networks when migrating physical servers, applications, or data to virtual servers?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_b9dd2eb0-fb97-457a-850d-b48270172101"><title>VMM Security - Hypervisor Hardening</title><label>IVS-11</label><description><p id="_8155ed5f-2e40-4527-8e23-f3b73fed744f">Access to all hypervisor management functions or administrative consoles for systems hosting virtualized systems shall be restricted to personnel based upon the principle of least privilege and supported through technical controls (e.g., two-factor authentication, audit trails, IP address filtering, firewalls, and TLS encapsulated communications to the administrative consoles).</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_690d5806-f898-4888-a579-0065a5434205">Do you restrict personnel access to all hypervisor management functions or administrative consoles for systems hosting virtualized systems based on the principle of least privilege and supported through technical controls (e.g., two-factor authentication, audit trails, IP address filtering, firewalls and TLS-encapsulated communications to the administrative consoles)?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_d1757f55-c42d-4677-b523-93522f3ebb0e"><title>Wireless Security</title><label>IVS-12</label><description><p id="_34744c18-f802-4f09-b6e1-24a300fbb6b2">Policies and procedures shall be established, and supporting business processes and technical measures implemented, to protect wireless network environments, including the following:</p>
<ul id="_e3e7631e-85c6-4843-b2c1-d28b13573367">
  <li>
    <p id="_5717a02a-898f-40ca-8fcf-465af172e8f0">Perimeter firewalls implemented and configured to restrict unauthorized traffic</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_7e67d8ab-53ca-4089-9873-464c88d17dcb">Security settings enabled with strong encryption for authentication and transmission, replacing vendor default settings (e.g., encryption keys, passwords, and SNMP community strings)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_23a9779f-203f-4ba0-9eed-583bf60948e0">User access to wireless network devices restricted to authorized personnel</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_6552a3c2-4962-4b34-870c-4c32bfa261cd">The capability to detect the presence of unauthorized (rogue) wireless network devices for a timely disconnect from the network</p>
  </li>
</ul>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_85e566d2-5c0a-4c4a-ad63-72d785ab06c7">Are policies and procedures established and mechanisms configured and implemented to protect the wireless network environment perimeter and to restrict unauthorized wireless traffic?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_d8fc19ff-5bdf-421d-ae1f-cdf250c6fd64">Are policies and procedures established and mechanisms implemented to ensure wireless security settings are enabled with strong encryption for authentication and transmission, replacing vendor default settings (e.g., encryption keys, passwords, SNMP community strings)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_4fa0db07-9f93-4b9b-ac5b-715ebd0a3b04">Are policies and procedures established and mechanisms implemented to protect wireless network environments and detect the presence of unauthorized (rogue) network devices for a timely disconnect from the network?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_e4b79d2c-6803-4854-a4f8-04bff3967282"><title>Network Architecture</title><label>IVS-13</label><description><p id="_5a7d1cf6-9c10-4bf4-b354-0f106392e18b">Network architecture diagrams shall clearly identify high-risk environments and data flows that may have legal compliance impacts. Technical measures shall be implemented and shall apply defense-in-depth techniques (e.g., deep packet analysis, traffic throttling, and black-holing) for detection and timely response to network-based attacks associated with anomalous ingress or egress traffic patterns (e.g., MAC spoofing and ARP poisoning attacks) and/or distributed denial-of-service (DDoS) attacks.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_8ed8c5cf-415a-4ddb-ac2d-a6d4006377cc">Do your network architecture diagrams clearly identify high-risk environments and data flows that may have legal compliance impacts?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_dd6fe947-9597-49c1-a134-2b2a79f5dfcd">Do you implement technical measures and apply defense-in-depth techniques (e.g., deep packet analysis, traffic throttling and black-holing) for detection and timely response to network-based attacks associated with anomalous ingress or egress traffic patterns (e.g., MAC spoofing and ARP poisoning attacks) and/or distributed denial-of-service (DDoS) attacks?</p>
</verification></requirement></requirement>
<requirement id="_16ab37f8-619f-4006-b0d2-54c561217ad0" obligation="requirement"><title>Interoperability &amp; Portability</title><label>IPY</label><requirement id="_728e2114-74bc-4f4e-9275-cec7fa64d499"><title>APIs</title><label>IPY-01</label><description><p id="_f74a6941-8d2c-406d-b1e8-654e5e101d70">The provider shall use open and published APIs to ensure support for interoperability between components and to facilitate migrating applications.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_5f0b5008-21e1-44af-a83d-18512ad9ba33">Do you publish a list of all APIs available in the service and indicate which are standard and which are customized?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_b477ffac-c170-4ebe-aa67-7c482d4153a6"><title>Data Request</title><label>IPY-02</label><description><p id="_82467720-a990-48e8-ae1d-5369c0a38c83">All structured and unstructured data shall be available to the customer and provided to them upon request in an industry-standard format (e.g., .doc, .xls, .pdf, logs, and flat files).</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_4b993d9e-d1dc-477d-9f16-7f37b0d578ed">Is unstructured customer data available on request in an industry-standard format (e.g., .doc, .xls, or .pdf)?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_6ff71280-d8a8-48e5-9b4e-1c4634e158d0"><title>Policy &amp; Legal</title><label>IPY-03</label><description><p id="_1ad80e22-5f17-4e80-b691-0352c8d07508">Policies, procedures, and mutually-agreed upon provisions and/or terms shall be established to satisfy customer (tenant) requirements for service-to-service application (API) and information processing interoperability, and portability for application development and information exchange, usage, and integrity persistence.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_369fba1f-29cb-4402-a32c-20564aec1ca6">Do you provide policies and procedures (i.e. service level agreements) governing the use of APIs for interoperability between your service and third-party applications?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_d0878f32-669a-48cc-84f6-e29683a3519a">Do you provide policies and procedures (i.e. service level agreements) governing the migration of application data to and from your service?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_487b3f47-fec0-4993-b2d4-8ca463a07882"><title>Standardized Network Protocols</title><label>IPY-04</label><description><p id="_f5ac9772-a785-49b7-be94-fbf320c60b26">The provider shall use secure (e.g., non-clear text and authenticated) standardized network protocols for the import and export of data and to manage the service, and shall make available a document to consumers (tenants) detailing the relevant interoperability and portability standards that are involved.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_86bd1dba-8982-4c9a-8b8c-63da8e726ffd">Can data import, data export, and service management be conducted over secure (e.g., non-clear text and authenticated), industry accepted standardized network protocols?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_866332e9-ac53-400e-b0ce-0d65b8af771f">Do you provide consumers (tenants) with documentation detailing the relevant interoperability and portability network protocol standards that are involved?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_e71d9a98-9f60-478a-99d8-d739a8e3ad6c"><title>Virtualization</title><label>IPY-05</label><description><p id="_71bf31e1-6c64-481b-a281-40b98a656b90">The provider shall use an industry-recognized virtualization platform and standard virtualization formats (e.g., OVF) to help ensure interoperability, and shall have documented custom changes made to any hypervisor in use, and all solution-specific virtualization hooks, available for customer review.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_830b4eb7-a8b5-4629-a868-79c6b4d7a09b">Do you use an industry-recognized virtualization platform and standard virtualization formats (e.g., OVF) to help ensure interoperability?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_5b245bc8-9b7d-40a1-8bb0-4b9215cce80d">Do you have documented custom changes made to any hypervisor in use, and all solution-specific virtualization hooks available for customer review?</p>
</verification></requirement></requirement>
<requirement id="_338d7817-b4d6-4253-beda-6854ee930051" obligation="requirement"><title>Mobile Security</title><label>MOS</label><requirement id="_f0cd002c-b34b-42fb-b479-500479c8e9d9"><title>Anti-Malware</title><label>MOS-01</label><description><p id="_01f85f73-2fef-46f9-a1de-dfad0dc46407">Anti-malware awareness training, specific to mobile devices, shall be included in the provider’s information security awareness training.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_6962136f-9e08-4bc6-adee-1d53ad5bbc45">Do you provide anti-malware training specific to mobile devices as part of your information security awareness training?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_84ab2011-1af8-4b0e-8fca-72b26a430cef"><title>Application Stores</title><label>MOS-02</label><description><p id="_23ad4631-2604-431c-acea-703a0d88c9fb">A documented list of approved application stores has been communicated as acceptable for mobile devices accessing or storing provider managed data.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_8bbd8b99-e237-45ab-9aff-3ca9588d142a">Do you document and make available lists of approved application stores for mobile devices accessing or storing company data and/or company systems?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_442adc7c-0dbc-437d-9f0d-3e80ec47ac5d"><title>Approved Applications</title><label>MOS-03</label><description><p id="_9cfb5a7c-1cc5-4fdf-8128-3c033fa1d7c4">The company shall have a documented policy prohibiting the installation of non-approved applications or approved applications not obtained through a pre-identified application store.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_a579d759-bb95-4ecc-a1a0-1a3018d7b0ae">Do you have a policy enforcement capability (e.g., XACML) to ensure that only approved applications and those from approved application stores can be loaded onto a mobile device?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_3dc3ef04-f4e4-4fad-b534-4d125201a996"><title>Approved Software for BYOD</title><label>MOS-04</label><description><p id="_7ea6b813-745e-4e28-9d90-05dcda6644bf">The BYOD policy and supporting awareness training clearly states the approved applications, application stores, and application extensions and plugins that may be used for BYOD usage.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_c63fefca-4757-4032-9752-b46b251d9514">Does your BYOD policy and training clearly state which applications and applications stores are approved for use on BYOD devices?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_49b2fcf1-7cf6-4f2c-a4cd-512e01572b8c"><title>Awareness and Training</title><label>MOS-05</label><description><p id="_fa62e020-b815-498d-af93-b91d9532d253">The provider shall have a documented mobile device policy that includes a documented definition for mobile devices and the acceptable usage and requirements for all mobile devices. The provider shall post and communicate the policy and requirements through the company’s security awareness and training program.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_35c868df-f6a5-47e0-813c-e12329e676f0">Do you have a documented mobile device policy in your employee training that clearly defines mobile devices and the accepted usage and requirements for mobile devices?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_a497ef07-b574-4096-b2ef-56b34aa1e0fb"><title>Cloud Based Services</title><label>MOS-06</label><description><p id="_d3630af2-25aa-41d0-b03b-f814221e42ad">All cloud-based services used by the company’s mobile devices or BYOD shall be pre-approved for usage and the storage of company business data.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_ecc5f653-af84-465f-9ffe-470ae8bd1d27">Do you have a documented list of pre-approved cloud based services that are allowed to be used for use and storage of company business data via a mobile device?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_90288ea8-bd81-4ad5-9a79-d8a0f134936f"><title>Compatibility</title><label>MOS-07</label><description><p id="_d1bcc41a-0511-4627-b9c0-76ee723bd5d1">The company shall have a documented application validation process to test for mobile device, operating system, and application compatibility issues.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_20fe5dfe-4f35-4a70-a6ad-a92cc868444b">Do you have a documented application validation process for testing device, operating system, and application compatibility issues?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_e0f61ded-c75f-4061-a926-0e5d208e7e0a"><title>Device Eligibility</title><label>MOS-08</label><description><p id="_7e2b6aac-64e0-4a27-8f8c-c3941df21932">The BYOD policy shall define the device and eligibility requirements to allow for BYOD usage.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_2abffac9-2b95-4247-b4b4-9f2c6fdc4af9">Do you have a BYOD policy that defines the device(s) and eligibility requirements allowed for BYOD usage?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_21a41597-4c7a-427f-b81b-f0b0bbc7f43e"><title>Device Inventory</title><label>MOS-09</label><description><p id="_86f86478-0735-4b16-ad5b-738c8cc0cbc8">An inventory of all mobile devices used to store and access company data shall be kept and maintained. All changes to the status of these devices, (i.e., operating system and patch levels, lost or decommissioned status, and to whom the device is assigned or approved for usage (BYOD)), will be included for each device in the inventory.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_77148e99-6461-4e67-8f9c-eabb2e9473fd">Do you maintain an inventory of all mobile devices storing and accessing company data which includes device status (e.g., operating system and patch levels, lost or decommissioned, device assignee)?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_b0781b0b-41a4-4121-92b9-74fd26ca2d16"><title>Device Management</title><label>MOS-10</label><description><p id="_577406b4-dca7-4252-8903-836149d69fff">A centralized, mobile device management solution shall be deployed to all mobile devices permitted to store, transmit, or process customer data.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_00d438db-ad30-4a24-b894-93ded79ca848">Do you have a centralized mobile device management solution deployed to all mobile devices that are permitted to store, transmit, or process company data?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_4143bae1-9131-4aef-9348-30892aaa558e"><title>Encryption</title><label>MOS-11</label><description><p id="_65f35387-ddee-48cc-b7bf-123f5a0e9a27">The mobile device policy shall require the use of encryption either for the entire device or for data identified as sensitive on all mobile devices and shall be enforced through technology controls.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_480de336-67da-461c-92ed-2d67118d32ac">Does your mobile device policy require the use of encryption for either the entire device or for data identified as sensitive enforceable through technology controls for all mobile devices?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_82811cd7-d2cc-46a4-9f32-a3a483cdc9eb"><title>Jailbreaking and Rooting</title><label>MOS-12</label><description><p id="_4b00af2e-8370-4ac9-913f-f77c389e5361">The mobile device policy shall prohibit the circumvention of built-in security controls on mobile devices (e.g., jailbreaking or rooting) and is enforced through detective and preventative controls on the device or through a centralized device management system (e.g., mobile device management).</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_7a1ad02e-6fdb-45d8-b2ef-7d6c6883179f">Does your mobile device policy prohibit the circumvention of built-in security controls on mobile devices (e.g., jailbreaking or rooting)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_6d6a39b6-fd1e-4285-9ecf-5fdabd63df1c">Do you have detective and preventative controls on the device or via a centralized device management system which prohibit the circumvention of built-in security controls?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_cf3e97b2-9a21-47ad-baf7-dbc7314a9b10"><title>Legal</title><label>MOS-13</label><description><p id="_3c061b41-5dc8-4ef5-b397-205743bbbe61">The BYOD policy includes clarifying language for the expectation of privacy, requirements for litigation, e-discovery, and legal holds. The BYOD policy shall clearly state the expectations over the loss of non-company data in the case that a wipe of the device is required.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_de6d8fd2-8788-4296-a5e0-d41a8104af79">Does your BYOD policy clearly define the expectation of privacy, requirements for litigation, e-discovery, and legal holds?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_2c0e687b-2069-4fad-8bb8-d3ec1bf43fa4">Do you have detective and preventative controls on the device or via a centralized device management system which prohibit the circumvention of built-in security controls?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_93066769-7161-4d03-a9c8-673ee406d6e7"><title>Lockout Screen</title><label>MOS-14</label><description><p id="_eee76965-95c3-4957-af2e-bdd63e135df7">BYOD and/or company owned devices are configured to require an automatic lockout screen, and the requirement shall be enforced through technical controls.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_a82186f7-d24b-4d1e-8bd1-861b85581dbb">Do you require and enforce via technical controls an automatic lockout screen for BYOD and company owned devices?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_c86d7d14-2163-4f83-9d12-05496eb7bee6"><title>Operating Systems</title><label>MOS-15</label><description><p id="_c6850190-55a2-4f2e-ab20-0070481b6dd1">Changes to mobile device operating systems, patch levels, and/or applications shall be managed through the company’s change management processes.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_4b72601c-67b6-4218-98c7-7c4b04866926">Do you manage all changes to mobile device operating systems, patch levels, and applications via your company’s change management processes?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_0a277d72-6343-4cf1-9e17-6523761c8909"><title>Passwords</title><label>MOS-16</label><description><p id="_9b433e74-8a21-4d6a-81f1-3066d7586286">Password policies, applicable to mobile devices, shall be documented and enforced through technical controls on all company devices or devices approved for BYOD usage, and shall prohibit the changing of password/PIN lengths and authentication requirements.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_a6dbd66a-5e42-43ea-b5c4-71d5471e2a77">Do you have password policies for enterprise issued mobile devices and/or BYOD mobile devices?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_f155d656-527a-4d25-ac50-d15df1a0aa4d">Are your password policies enforced through technical controls (i.e. MDM)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_06f0bef2-cc6d-42d7-82f5-eac1787add2d">Do your password policies prohibit the changing of authentication requirements (i.e. password/PIN length) via a mobile device?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_c046569a-4617-4f29-8375-c620f7641196"><title>Policy</title><label>MOS-17</label><description><p id="_d4217364-4caa-412b-a8eb-eca890ecd1b3">The mobile device policy shall require the BYOD user to perform backups of data, prohibit the usage of unapproved application stores, and require the use of anti-malware software (where supported).</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_bdbd7783-6ceb-41bd-ab61-97dd3b8649ea">Do you have a policy that requires BYOD users to perform backups of specified corporate data?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_d6fc5cbc-7e02-4190-881b-f641cc3eacb2">Do you have a policy that requires BYOD users to prohibit the usage of unapproved application stores?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_318baaeb-0b1b-4825-af15-7558d035c656">Do you have a policy that requires BYOD users to use anti-malware software (where supported)?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_daff92c3-4ca9-4597-be26-aee3c9f5e27a"><title>Remote Wipe</title><label>MOS-18</label><description><p id="_1fb42458-084b-4cd0-9968-5bf0225b0c7f">All mobile devices permitted for use through the company BYOD program or a company-assigned mobile device shall allow for remote wipe by the company’s corporate IT or shall have all company-provided data wiped by the company’s corporate IT.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_a6802f1b-add2-4275-bb2b-efd50549acc3">Does your IT provide remote wipe or corporate data wipe for all company-accepted BYOD devices?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_f0bb1813-fa1e-4add-9da9-5b4fe10c251c">Does your IT provide remote wipe or corporate data wipe for all company-assigned mobile devices?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_f6c4e4bd-a989-49ca-8134-10074dd4f323"><title>Security Patches</title><label>MOS-19</label><description><p id="_0c6b342e-3ca2-4494-bbb1-f8ccb507cc6d">Mobile devices connecting to corporate networks or storing and accessing company information shall allow for remote software version/patch validation. All mobile devices shall have the latest available security-related patches installed upon general release by the device manufacturer or carrier and authorized IT personnel shall be able to perform these updates remotely.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_b75cec96-6291-4ffe-b951-d55742082d8e">Do your mobile devices have the latest available security-related patches installed upon general release by the device manufacturer or carrier?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_f4dfd0d8-6342-4a00-b02f-116136b749d7">Do your mobile devices allow for remote validation to download the latest security patches by company IT personnel?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_309964d6-72bd-4bc4-a7a5-3c52441a4aaa"><title>Users</title><label>MOS-20</label><description><p id="_bbe945fa-6a67-4697-83a5-90fb6671506e">The BYOD policy shall clarify the systems and servers allowed for use or access on a BYOD-enabled device.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_38035fef-328e-4ff9-8fe0-24c7b3185449">Does your BYOD policy clarify the systems and servers allowed for use or access on the BYOD-enabled device?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_078e89a3-6496-4467-aff9-c992d20b1933">Does your BYOD policy specify the user roles that are allowed access via a BYOD-enabled device?</p>
</verification></requirement></requirement>
<requirement id="_f2b9c085-2e76-4837-a42f-d15471f81607" obligation="requirement"><title>Security Incident Management, E-Discovery, &amp; Cloud Forensics</title><label>SEF</label><requirement id="_7f9144c7-2826-4184-aaaa-04df67d22ee4"><title>Contact / Authority Maintenance</title><label>SEF-01</label><description><p id="_4b158af5-4212-43f7-a428-0a079d36d3b3">Points of contact for applicable regulation authorities, national and local law enforcement, and other legal jurisdictional authorities shall be maintained and regularly updated (e.g., change in impacted-scope and/or a change in any compliance obligation) to ensure direct compliance liaisons have been established and to be prepared for a forensic investigation requiring rapid engagement with law enforcement.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_af575292-1bb7-402f-9487-375da839ec22">Do you maintain liaisons and points of contact with local authorities in accordance with contracts and appropriate regulations?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_2c683ccd-2768-40af-9b84-a4fa4c553639"><title>Incident Management</title><label>SEF-02</label><description><p id="_4dc4192a-272b-4ea7-bde4-273ce7120caa">Policies and procedures shall be established, and supporting business processes and technical measures implemented, to triage security-related events and ensure timely and thorough incident management, as per established IT service management policies and procedures.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_8b94cf8e-48d2-4c98-b7c1-2508396bdeab">Do you have a documented security incident response plan?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_6ebc98e0-1963-4a99-beb7-0018c9dd54db">Do you integrate customized tenant requirements into your security incident response plans?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_6a66f9df-1f9b-4d57-9d88-907e41001ede">Do you publish a roles and responsibilities document specifying what you vs. your tenants are responsible for during security incidents?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_9a678568-204b-4876-9122-cec51bab7e2d">Have you tested your security incident response plans in the last year?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_89c46ee9-c0b2-405d-9a93-b191158fd35a"><title>Incident Reporting</title><label>SEF-03</label><description><p id="_b407bb68-e50b-4ad0-8b41-dc21c1fb9cd1">Workforce personnel and external business relationships shall be informed of their responsibility and, if required, shall consent and/or contractually agree to report all information security events in a timely manner. Information security events shall be reported through predefined communications channels in a timely manner adhering to applicable legal, statutory, or regulatory compliance obligations.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_6369707e-a351-40c1-bf10-9ddb91ba63d3">Does your security information and event management (SIEM) system merge data sources (e.g., app logs, firewall logs, IDS logs, physical access logs, etc.) for granular analysis and alerting?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_53d6aeef-2162-4f40-9bc0-e33b573cdb6a">Does your logging and monitoring framework allow isolation of an incident to specific tenants?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_2c5c227f-1856-4626-a8df-746ba2ca337a"><title>Incident Response Legal Preparation</title><label>SEF-04</label><description><p id="_5d162dfd-9249-4908-adb5-52aaae8f610f">Proper forensic procedures, including chain of custody, are required for the presentation of evidence to support potential legal action subject to the relevant jurisdiction after an information security incident. Upon notification, customers and/or other external business partners impacted by a security breach shall be given the opportunity to participate as is legally permissible in the forensic investigation.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_d9f4498a-745a-44e1-aaf8-d0eb2ea0cc6d">Does your incident response plan comply with industry standards for legally admissible chain-of-custody management processes and controls?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_153eab8c-4e88-41b4-a588-6541ccafdd8b">Does your incident response capability include the use of legally admissible forensic data collection and analysis techniques?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_d4de8604-1318-472f-b5e8-95990f95eb38">Are you capable of supporting litigation holds (freeze of data from a specific point in time) for a specific tenant without freezing other tenant data?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_184be2bd-41fc-4e35-941e-854012d165f4">Do you enforce and attest to tenant data separation when producing data in response to legal subpoenas?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_75c58254-cd38-4073-92ef-3004ac711e2c"><title>Incident Response Metrics</title><label>SEF-05</label><description><p id="_685d6944-6b2e-4ce3-a8b0-377455165e0a">Mechanisms shall be put in place to monitor and quantify the types, volumes, and costs of information security incidents.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_45a6a105-5d97-48c2-a841-aa0a24f26b2f">Do you monitor and quantify the types, volumes, and impacts on all information security incidents?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_1eea97e1-6a0b-481c-9304-2054102ca4d6">Will you share statistical information for security incident data with your tenants upon request?</p>
</verification></requirement></requirement>
<requirement id="_2de4c66f-c18d-4f29-9087-f52003d977aa" obligation="requirement"><title>Supply Chain Management, Transparency, and Accountability</title><label>STA</label><requirement id="_9cbf438d-50fe-451a-9771-db40d602bebf"><title>Data Quality and Integrity</title><label>STA-01</label><description><p id="_6e33d066-8ac9-4e4c-8af9-3f66ddcb2439">Providers shall inspect, account for, and work with their cloud supply-chain partners to correct data quality errors and associated risks. Providers shall design and implement controls to mitigate and contain data security risks through proper separation of duties, role-based access, and least-privilege access for all personnel within their supply chain.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_b7c4f4e6-0c86-4608-b322-aa6ef0d40d06">Do you inspect and account for data quality errors and associated risks, and work with your cloud supply-chain partners to correct them?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_bf0c8692-2aef-4e9f-9b24-67654165fb3f">Do you design and implement controls to mitigate and contain data security risks through proper separation of duties, role-based access, and least-privileged access for all personnel within your supply chain?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_ae584597-9e4e-4903-be84-3db163476536"><title>Incident Reporting</title><label>STA-02</label><description><p id="_ecf279e7-c49f-406b-8243-51b45acdc0b3">The provider shall make security incident information available to all affected customers and providers periodically through electronic methods (e.g., portals).</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_8c3af304-4cc2-45ed-90f5-30c164d2a372">Do you make security incident information available to all affected customers and providers periodically through electronic methods (e.g., portals)?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_5e16c42c-19f7-47a3-81cf-aee612e3830f"><title>Network / Infrastructure Services</title><label>STA-03</label><description><p id="_6b6576d4-4e61-49b2-b366-3a15f405727e">Business-critical or customer (tenant) impacting (physical and virtual) application and system-system interface (API) designs and configurations, and infrastructure network and systems components, shall be designed, developed, and deployed in accordance with mutually agreed-upon service and capacity-level expectations, as well as IT governance and service management policies and procedures.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_73889c6f-0de3-4f1a-8349-e7aab20f7091">Do you collect capacity and use data for all relevant components of your cloud service offering?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_e1eafbaa-be06-45fd-a2cf-c00fe7ee5ac9">Do you provide tenants with capacity planning and use reports?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_903fde4e-8610-44c0-bc39-4f1eef0cf8ad"><title>Provider Internal Assessments</title><label>STA-04</label><description><p id="_d29822c0-fdd6-44ec-8ba5-14aa11533b6d">The provider shall perform annual internal assessments of conformance and effectiveness of its policies, procedures, and supporting measures and metrics.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_b9c1c46e-8cdc-4a8a-9f9b-5cd0e767b436">Do you perform annual internal assessments of conformance and effectiveness of your policies, procedures, and supporting measures and metrics?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_a4a0b8b8-30b6-42d4-8660-baf9501e9a02"><title>Third Party Agreements</title><label>STA-05</label><description><p id="_4812b6a8-806b-414b-93f8-d006561d4ff4">Supply chain agreements (e.g., SLAs) between providers and customers (tenants) shall incorporate at least the following mutually-agreed upon provisions and/or terms:</p>
<ul id="_c41334c3-d86c-4ff2-9f89-6a4fde1ba2b8">
  <li>
    <p id="_d8e40332-b277-4fd1-be88-c1e2a972df84">Scope of business relationship and services offered (e.g., customer (tenant) data acquisition, exchange and usage, feature sets and functionality, personnel and infrastructure network and systems components for service delivery and support, roles and responsibilities of provider and customer (tenant) and any subcontracted or outsourced business relationships, physical geographical location of hosted services, and any known regulatory compliance considerations)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_5cbe5204-c9ad-4c6a-93f2-f4042dc1d0b9">Information security requirements, provider and customer (tenant) primary points of contact for the duration of the business relationship, and references to detailed supporting and relevant business processes and technical measures implemented to enable effectively governance, risk management, assurance and legal, statutory and regulatory compliance obligations by all impacted business relationships</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_b223160d-93df-40e9-8f86-aac34392fe4b">Notification and/or pre-authorization of any changes controlled by the provider with customer (tenant) impacts</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_725fdd12-85fd-41ce-8b49-f38ffe00472b">Timely notification of a security incident (or confirmed breach) to all customers (tenants) and other business relationships impacted (i.e., up- and down-stream impacted supply chain)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_b22ac421-a0b1-43b7-b47a-79ae45d01f0a">Assessment and independent verification of compliance with agreement provisions and/or terms (e.g., industry-acceptable certification, attestation audit report, or equivalent forms of assurance) without posing an unacceptable business risk of exposure to the organization being assessed</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_e1a74501-54b6-400f-92e7-a58923639d36">Expiration of the business relationship and treatment of customer (tenant) data impacted</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p id="_d93638b7-bbd7-4950-8b5b-2b1915afeb91">Customer (tenant) service-to-service application (API) and data interoperability and portability requirements for application development and information exchange, usage, and integrity persistence</p>
  </li>
</ul>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_3c887fde-1298-4f32-9eeb-b8344d03037e">Do you select and monitor outsourced providers in compliance with laws in the country where the data is processed, stored, and transmitted?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_d89264ae-bc30-4f66-855a-87509d725e6b">Do you select and monitor outsourced providers in compliance with laws in the country where the data originates?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_2062d72e-1ac8-4c46-9d36-18ad7bcb3e90">Does legal counsel review all third-party agreements?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_44e5f146-555c-47ff-a7b3-693241ad2772">Do third-party agreements include provision for the security and protection of information and assets?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_779d53c7-54ba-4e68-98e5-66fc8474835d">Do you provide the client with a list and copies of all subprocessing agreements and keep this updated?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_71eac67e-a228-4f42-b849-b2931d08fb41"><title>Supply Chain Governance Reviews</title><label>STA-06</label><description><p id="_a332711c-2db0-4a38-acae-8c64a7fc82cb">Providers shall review the risk management and governance processes of their partners so that practices are consistent and aligned to account for risks inherited from other members of that partner’s cloud supply chain.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_16396644-1f8c-4761-8551-6d6c0f2171fc">Do you review the risk management and governanced processes of partners to account for risks inherited from other members of that partner’s supply chain?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_884c17b9-1624-40a3-abaf-f932289c5aec"><title>Supply Chain Metrics</title><label>STA-07</label><description><p id="_f8858dd4-c3ae-41bb-9b17-34e84cdc36bb">Policies and procedures shall be implemented to ensure the consistent review of service agreements (e.g., SLAs) between providers and customers (tenants) across the relevant supply chain (upstream/downstream). Reviews shall be performed at least annually and identify non-conformance to established agreements. The reviews should result in actions to address service-level conflicts or inconsistencies resulting from disparate supplier relationships.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_2b8dc7d6-a42d-42e4-9243-2e20b16c3c18">Are policies and procedures established, and supporting business processes and technical measures implemented, for maintaining complete, accurate, and relevant agreements (e.g., SLAs) between providers and customers (tenants)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_0bbd3835-5071-4d2f-b0fc-607afbbfab99">Do you have the ability to measure and address non-conformance of provisions and/or terms across the entire supply chain (upstream/downstream)?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_9b2243a6-5912-4ba3-825e-52f22b5c238a">Can you manage service-level conflicts or inconsistencies resulting from disparate supplier relationships?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_47583eba-6647-4ba6-92ed-82669483152f">Do you review all agreements, policies, and processes at least annually?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_74e6ccb6-f868-400d-9cdf-faf79b7349f1"><title>Third Party Assessment</title><label>STA-08</label><description><p id="_81794e22-97b7-4adf-968c-94758453cdf5">Providers shall assure reasonable information security across their information supply chain by performing an annual review. The review shall include all partners/third party providers upon which their information supply chain depends on.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_ed65a669-1aa5-4f4b-8f9b-8caaba7b502e">Do you assure reasonable information security across your information supply chain by performing an annual review?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_40bb08f7-2c3a-4f8c-9079-259e8abcd4a1">Does your annual review include all partners/third-party providers upon which your information supply chain depends?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_77b7d526-2005-4b15-a904-ab816fa2115c"><title>Third Party Audits</title><label>STA-09</label><description><p id="_cdaf6241-93ec-43fa-8d35-e93bad6e5ce1">Third-party service providers shall demonstrate compliance with information security and confidentiality, access control, service definitions, and delivery level agreements included in third-party contracts. Third-party reports, records, and services shall undergo audit and review at least annually to govern and maintain compliance with the service delivery agreements.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_02e5f98f-b24c-40bf-a576-4dee6225610b">Do you permit tenants to perform independent vulnerability assessments?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_c845dbd3-a2c2-46c5-b35f-ce7d0eee1a0c">Do you have external third party services conduct vulnerability scans and periodic penetration tests on your applications and networks?</p>
</verification></requirement></requirement>
<requirement id="_0b5cf976-efc2-4c4d-adff-ae8c93b48d99" obligation="requirement"><title>Threat and Vulnerability Management</title><label>TVM</label><requirement id="_7c895db8-609a-4781-9df5-e3a119b4e84a"><title>Antivirus / Malicious Software</title><label>TVM-01</label><description><p id="_90db766d-8bd7-4d79-906e-95abed89a87b">Policies and procedures shall be established, and supporting business processes and technical measures implemented, to prevent the execution of malware on organizationally-owned or managed user end-point devices (i.e., issued workstations, laptops, and mobile devices) and IT infrastructure network and systems components.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_b00d96f5-c752-4114-a143-10757bfd3fab">Do you have anti-malware programs that support or connect to your cloud service offerings installed on all of your systems?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_04faf356-db93-48fb-a83c-8f8c73fc0ee4">Do you ensure that security threat detection systems using signatures, lists, or behavioral patterns are updated across all infrastructure components within industry accepted time frames?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_a7710432-6407-4b77-aca2-2495b723a795"><title>Vulnerability / Patch Management</title><label>TVM-02</label><description><p id="_69fe4401-de84-4e80-b084-bfcbd4ddee6a">Policies and procedures shall be established, and supporting processes and technical measures implemented, for timely detection of vulnerabilities within organizationally-owned or managed applications, infrastructure network and system components (e.g., network vulnerability assessment, penetration testing) to ensure the efficiency of implemented security controls. A risk-based model for prioritizing remediation of identified vulnerabilities shall be used. Changes shall be managed through a change management process for all vendor-supplied patches, configuration changes, or changes to the organization’s internally developed software. Upon request, the provider informs customer (tenant) of policies and procedures and identified weaknesses especially if customer (tenant) data is used as part the service and/or customer (tenant) has some shared responsibility over implementation of control.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_4993aec7-409b-4766-bd45-becdc2ff1977">Do you conduct network-layer vulnerability scans regularly as prescribed by industry best practices?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_6ed70228-2543-48a6-8695-57028df0810b">Do you conduct application-layer vulnerability scans regularly as prescribed by industry best practices?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_c69d83de-1c57-46f8-82b0-93c9fc6a59fc">Do you conduct local operating system-layer vulnerability scans regularly as prescribed by industry best practices?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_333e66ae-6b91-4d81-b0ad-088d392fdbdd">Will you make the results of vulnerability scans available to tenants at their request?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_be59eebb-6544-4274-a6e4-88cb16565cd1">Do you have a capability to rapidly patch vulnerabilities across all of your computing devices, applications, and systems?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_725ecbee-6577-45a0-965e-697d658d5f99">Will you provide your risk-based systems patching time frames to your tenants upon request?</p>
</verification></requirement>
<requirement id="_5a58df99-2484-4540-87f0-6d32adbdb8c5"><title>Mobile Code</title><label>TVM-03</label><description><p id="_7fdc4030-3bec-416d-9cb7-5d3fbc3c5357">Policies and procedures shall be established, and supporting business processes and technical measures implemented, to prevent the execution of unauthorized mobile code, defined as software transferred between systems over a trusted or untrusted network and executed on a local system without explicit installation or execution by the recipient, on organizationally-owned or managed user end-point devices (e.g., issued workstations, laptops, and mobile devices) and IT infrastructure network and systems components.</p>
</description><verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_4f43c47d-ea6e-460f-8f8e-28aa050328a0">Is mobile code authorized before its installation and use, and the code configuration checked, to ensure that the authorized mobile code operates according to a clearly defined security policy?</p>
</verification>
<verification exclude="false" type="general">
  <p id="_b68d0d0f-6a1a-40a2-8da3-2b024b3c9378">Is all unauthorized mobile code prevented from executing?</p>
</verification></requirement></requirement></clause>

</sections><annex id="_revision_history" obligation="normative">
  <title>Revision History</title>
  <table id="_ee0fc616-02eb-4e0c-ada5-956da4a0f8ea">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th align="left">Date</th>
      <th align="left">Release</th>
      <th align="left">Editor</th>
      <th align="left">Primary clauses modified</th>
      <th align="left">Description</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td align="left">2016-04-28</td>
      <td align="left">0.1</td>
      <td align="left">G. Editor</td>
      <td align="left">all</td>
      <td align="left">initial version</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
</annex><bibliography><references id="_normative_references" obligation="informative"><title>Normative References</title>
<bibitem type="international-standard" id="ISO19101-1">
  <fetched>2019-06-11</fetched>
  <title format="text/plain" language="en" script="Latn">Geographic information — Reference model — Part 1: Fundamentals</title>
  <title format="text/plain" language="fr" script="Latn">Information géographique — Modèle de référence — Partie 1: Principes de base</title>
  <uri type="src">https://www.iso.org/standard/59164.html</uri>
  <uri type="obp">https://www.iso.org/obp/ui/#!iso:std:59164:en</uri>
  <uri type="rss">https://www.iso.org/contents/data/standard/05/91/59164.detail.rss</uri>
  <docidentifier type="ISO">ISO 19101-1:2014</docidentifier>
  <date type="published">
    <on>2014</on>
  </date>
  <contributor>
    <role type="publisher"/>
    <organization>
      <name>International Organization for Standardization</name>
      <abbreviation>ISO</abbreviation>
      <uri>www.iso.org</uri>
    </organization>
  </contributor>
  <edition>1</edition>
  <language>en</language>
  <language>fr</language>
  <script>Latn</script>
  <abstract format="plain" language="en" script="Latn">ISO 19101-1:2014 defines the reference model for standardization in the field of geographic information. This reference model describes the notion of interoperability and sets forth the fundamentals by which this standardization takes place.Although structured in the context of information technology and information technology standards, ISO 19101-1:2014 is independent of any application development method or technology implementation approach.</abstract>
  <abstract format="plain" language="fr" script="Latn">l’ISO 19101-1:2014 définit le modèle de référence pour la normalisation dans le domaine de l’information géographique. Ce modèle de référence décrit la notion d’interopérabilité et établit les principes de base sur lesquels s’appuiera la normalisation.Bien que l’ISO 19101-1:2014 soit définie dans le contexte des technologies de l’information et des normes s’y rapportant, elle ne dépend d’aucune méthode de développement d’applications, ni d’aucune approche de mise en ?uvre de technologie.</abstract>
  <status>
    <stage>60</stage>
    <substage>60</substage>
  </status>
  <copyright>
    <from>2014</from>
    <owner>
      <organization>
        <name>ISO</name>
      </organization>
    </owner>
  </copyright>
  <relation type="obsoletes">
    <bibitem>
      <formattedref>ISO 19101:2002</formattedref>
    </bibitem>
  </relation>
  <editorialgroup>
    <technical-committee number="211" type="TC">ISO/TC 211Geographic information/Geomatics</technical-committee>
  </editorialgroup>
  <ics>
    <code>35.240.70</code>
    <text>IT applications in science</text>
  </ics>
</bibitem> </references><references id="Bibliography" obligation="informative"><title>Bibliography</title><note id="_c1dc2c19-adbb-403d-8a18-f3c295ad4b8f"><p id="_29317e69-ad6e-48f9-9394-116e4420fd49">The TC has approved Springer LNCS as the official document citation type.</p>
<p id="_3cd897ff-4554-40dc-81d1-09f795ba53bf">Springer LNCS is widely used in technical and computer science journals and other publications</p>

<p id="_e96fdb71-2a12-4f85-9a1b-33533bec1298">– Actual References:</p>
<p id="_7773e08e-8a10-4844-8928-12db4dc97afa">[n] Journal: Author Surname, A.: Title. Publication Title. Volume number, Issue number, Pages Used (Year Published)</p>
<p id="_e5cbbdb7-9828-4aaa-b3ce-8ee3fb531969">[n] Web: Author Surname, A.: Title, <link target="http://Website-Url"/></p></note>
<bibitem id="CSA2015">
  <formattedref format="application/x-isodoc+xml"><em>CSA: CSA Testbed 12 Annex B: Architecture</em> (2015).</formattedref>
  <docidentifier>CSATB12</docidentifier>
</bibitem></references></bibliography>
</csand-standard>
